<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An exposition in the epistell of Iude the apostel of Christ wherein he setteth playnly before euery mans eyes false apostels, and theyr craftes, by ye which they haue longe receyued symple christian people.</title>
            <author>Ridley, Lancelot, d. 1576.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1538</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 131 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 75 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10772</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21042</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104543</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840278</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840278</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4760</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10772)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4760)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 142:16, 1557:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An exposition in the epistell of Iude the apostel of Christ wherein he setteth playnly before euery mans eyes false apostels, and theyr craftes, by ye which they haue longe receyued symple christian people.</title>
                  <author>Ridley, Lancelot, d. 1576.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[148] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[Imprynted in the house of Thomas Gybson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1538]]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Lancelot Ridley.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from colophon; publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 21042a on UMI microfilm reel 1557.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-H I¹⁰.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the British Library and the Cambridge University Library.</note>
                  <note>Appears at reel 142 # 16 (British Library copy), and at reel 1557 #3 (Cambridge University Library copy).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Jude --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4760:1"/>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:4760:1"/>
               <figure>
                  <p>¶ An expoſition in the epiſtell of Iude the apoſtel of Chriſt wherein he ſetteth playnly before eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry mans eyes falſe apoſtels, and theyr craftes, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which they haue longe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued ſymple chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian people.</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="argument">
            <pb facs="tcp:4760:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>¶ The argument.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N thys pyſtell Iude monyſheth men to ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke hede and beware of pſeudapoſtels, and of theyr falſe doctryne ſhewynge &amp; perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge to all men, that god wyll not ſuffer theſe pſeudapoſtels, and al them that aſſenteth and agreeth to their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyuable doctryne, and folow them in maners of lyuynge to eſcape vnpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſhed. And that men ſhall knowe theſe pſeudapoſtels, that they may be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ware of them the better, and of theyr lyenge doctryne, whiche bryngeth to confuſion and dampnation, Iude de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribeth theſe pſeudapoſtils, &amp; ſheweth certayne of theyr propertyes, by the which they may be knowen, although they go craftyly to warke, and ſleyght<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly hathe crepte in amonge men, with
<pb facs="tcp:4760:2"/>
moche fayned and pretenſed holynes, pretendyng in wordes to ſeke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glory of god, the auancement of his worde, the profyte of other, whan they ſeke theyr owne glory, theyr owne auance<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment, theyr owne profyte, lucre and aua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tage. Iude threteth to theſe pſeud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>apoſtels, and to all theyr adherentes &amp; folowers of theyr falſe and deceyua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble doctryne, euerlaſtyng woo, payne and dampnation, that he myght dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade them from ſynne &amp; deuyllyſhe doctryne, yf not for loue, yet for feare of punyſhment: for god wyl not ſuffer ſynne to be vnpunyſhed. Of theſe pſeudapoſtels, and of their deceyuable doctryne vſed, in the pyſtell you may ſe and reade, this is the ſomme of the pyſtell. But I praye you reade this pyſtell to your edyfyenge and admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition to beware of falſe doctryne, as the author of this expoſition in this pyſtell of Iude wylleth and deſyreth
<pb facs="tcp:4760:3"/>
and ſetteth forth this rude and homely expoſition for that intent onely, that theſe that be vnlerned myght ſe and perceyue the better, with what decey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uable doctryne men haue ben deluded and deceyued many a daye, that men myght receyue Chriſtis doctryne and of his apoſtelles, whiche bryngeth to lyfe, ioye, and blyſſe, and leue the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryn of pſeudapoſtelles, whiche bryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth to deathe, to hell, and to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyll. Folowe Chriſt &amp; his doctryne and you ſhall haue lyfe with hym in glorye. To hym be glorye alwaye.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:4760:3"/>
            <head>¶ The piſtle of ſaynet Iude.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>das the ſeruaunt of Ieſus Chriſte, the broder of Iames, to them which are cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led and ſanctified in god the father, and preſerued in Chriſt Ieſus, mercy vnto you &amp; peace and loue be multiplied.</p>
            <p>They that wylleth and deſyreth to vnderſtande the holy ſcripture of god trewly, purely &amp; ſincerely, theſe thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges they muſt conſider, and euer haue before theyr eyes. Fyrſt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they knowe who ſpekes, for in holy ſcripture there be many that ſpekes, ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tymes ſpekes god, ſomtymes the deuyll, ſomtymes Chriſte and his apoſtilles, ſomtymes the ſcribes &amp; the phariſeis, ſomtymes Peter, ſomtymes Paule, ſomtymes Iudas, ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tymes Anna, Cayphas, and
<pb facs="tcp:4760:4"/>
Pylate, therfore it is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenient to con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſider who ſpekes, leſt one be taken to ſpeke, whan another ſpekes, as Chriſt to ſpeke, whan the deuyll ſpekes: or contrarye, the deuyll to ſpeke, whan Chriſt ſpekes, and ſo of the other. For although all holy ſcripture was writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by the ſpirite of god, whiche is the ſpirite of trewthe, yet there is in holy ſcripture that ſpekes many, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>as is ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed before, therfore it is mete to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider who ſpekes. Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly they muſt conſider, to whom ſpecially ſcripture dothe ſpeke, of what affection, diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and nature they be, to whom it is ſpoken. Thyrdly for what cauſe, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe and inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t the wordes of ſcripture chefely was ſpoken, and what the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gooſt wolde perſwade or diſſwade in that place of ſcripture, by thoſe that ſpekes. Finally what is the clere ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence and proper vnderſtandynge of that ſcripture ſpoken, that it may be
<pb facs="tcp:4760:4"/>
open, playne and euident to all men, what is the trewe ſence &amp; meanynge of the wordes of holy ſcripture in that place ſpoken. Theſe circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtances no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, the holy ſcripture ſhal be more ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyer to vnderſtande and knowe.</p>
            <p>The author that wrote this piſtle by the inſpiration of the holy gooſte was Iudas Thadeus, one of the .xii. apoſtels of Chriſt Ieſus, whom ſaynt Mathewe reckeneth amonges the .xii apoſtels of Chriſt. Math .x. But there was two men, that was called Iudas bothe apoſtilles of Chriſt, the one dyd appere to the outwarde opinion and eſtimation of men, to be entierly belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued &amp; hye in the fauour with his lorde and mayſter Chriſt Ieſus, ye and hyer in fauour than any of the other of the xii. apoſtels, Ye he dyd appere to be ſo hyghly beloued with Chryſte Ieſus, that he preferred hym before all other
<pb facs="tcp:4760:5"/>
of the apoſtels, and made hym as ſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde and ouerſeer of his houſe, and made hym his purſe bearer: yea alſo Chriſt wolde haue hym to be ſo nye &amp; familier with hym, that he wold haue hym to eate with hym, and to put his hande in Chriſtis dyſhe. But this Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das ſo hyghly beloued of his mayſter, lorde &amp; kynge Chriſt Ieſus, as an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynde, yea mooſt vnkynde of all, dyd betray his mayſter ſo louyng, kynde &amp; gentyl: and ſolde hym to the wicked &amp; cruel iewes to be crucified. This Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das that betrayed Chriſt was not the author of this pyſtell, for that Iudas was called Iudas Iſcharioth. There was an other called Iudas Lebbeꝰ or Thadeus, one of the apoſtils of Chriſt called the brother of our lorde Ieſus, becauſe he was the ſonne of the ſyſter to the mother of Chriſt, as is wrytten Marc. vi. This Iudas called the bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Chriſt was the author y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wrote
<pb facs="tcp:4760:5"/>
this piſtell, as the begynnynge of the piſtell dothe ſhewe. To whom it was written, the ſalutatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſheweth, to thoſe that were called, ſanctified &amp; preſerued in our lorde Ieſus Chryſte, for what cauſe &amp; intent this piſtel was written, what is conteyned in the piſtell, in the proceſſe of the piſtell, god wyllynge it ſhall be made open &amp; euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to al good chriſten reders, that with a pure harte &amp; ſtomacke in fayth deſyreth to knowe the wyll &amp; pleaſure of god, &amp; wyll take the paynes to rede this homely declara<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion of this holy &amp; ſpirituall pyſtell of ſaynet Iude, and marke diligently the holſome counſels &amp; ſpiritual leſſons y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſaynt Iudas teachethus in this piſtel. Saynt Iudas diuideth this piſtel in a ſalutatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; a narratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as lyra ſheweth after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> example of ſaynt Paule in his piſtels. In the ſalutation he ſheweth who was the author of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> piſtell, what was his office to do, to whom it was
<pb facs="tcp:4760:6"/>
written, what thynges he deſyreth to theym to whome he wrote this py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtel. The auctor vſeth a ſalutacyon in the begynning of his pyſtell after the faſſyon and maner of them that vſeth to wryt pyſtelles. And alſo leſſe any ſhulde counte hym without good hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manyte as to ſpeake to any of ſadde and weyghty matters, whom he dyd not ſalute at the left before. And alſo he vſeth this ſalutacyon, to teache vs Chriſten men and women one to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute an other, &amp; to deſyre, and wyſhe one to an other ſuche thynges as he deſyreth (that is to ſaye) the grace, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noure, peace, and mercye of God to be multyplyed to all Chriſten men and wemen. Iudas the ſeruaunt of Ieſus Chriſt. In theſe wordes is ſhewed who was the Author of this pyſtell (that is to ſaye) one Iudas not Iſearyoth the betrayer of Chriſt: but an other Iudas (by name Thadeus)
<pb facs="tcp:4760:6"/>
called the brother of Chriſt. Here ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue theſe two men, both called Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das both Apoſtles of Chriſt, the one of them to be good, the other euell. Here you maye learne good reader, no dyf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to be betwene a good man &amp; an euell man as touchynge their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes and offyces, as you do ſe the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of this pyſtel to be a good man, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeruaunte and the Apoſtle of Chriſte, althoughe he was called Iudas, and agreeth in name with hym that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed Chriſte, yet his name Iudas made hym not euell. So lyke wyſe Iudas Iſcarioth all thoughe be agre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in name with this Iudas, his name made hym not good. It is not the outwarde name ne offyce that ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth a man or woman good, but it is the grace of God, and perſeueraunce there in that maketh a man good. Therfore let vs learne, here not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes to iudge according to the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde
<pb facs="tcp:4760:7"/>
apperaunce. For yf we iudge after that facion we ſhall be deceyued yf any wolde iudge after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> outwarde apperaunce and after the opynyon of men, who wolde not iudge and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre Iudas the betrayer of Chriſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Iudas the author of this pyſtell, and ſaye that he was moche better man then was Iudas Thadeus, in that Chriſte made hym hys purſe bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer and ouerſeer of his houſe, &amp; ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to hym more fauoure, as dyd out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde appere, then he dyd to this Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das Thadeus. And yet Iudas Iſcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryoth was euell, and the chylde of per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dicyon. The other Iudas Thadeus was good, and the chylde of ſaluacy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, althoughe the iudgemente of the worlde was other wayes. Here lerne the iudgement of the worlde, and of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> outwarde apperaunce to the eye often tymes to be deceyuable, and deceyue men oftimes. Therfore fayth is not
<pb facs="tcp:4760:7"/>
alwayes to be geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> outward apperaunce, or to the opinyon of men. For men iudgeth theſe thynges that doth appere. God beholdeth the herte and the inwarde affection of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> minde. oftymes it chaunceth theſe to be leſte with God, and fardeſt from his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure, whome men doth iudge to be fyrſt and hyeſt in the fauoure of God. Paraduenture men iudgeth Popes, Cardynalles, Legates, Byſſhoppes, Archebyſhoppes, Abbottes, Decayns Prelates, Pryors, Monkes, Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, Preeſtes, Fryers obſeruantes, cartuſyans, and ſuche lyke to be more in fauoure with God then laye men, or lay women, when God peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture doth preferre laye men before all them. And more hath in his fauoure the poore ſymple lay man, or lay wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, then the hyeſt byſſhop, pope, or cardinall, for God is not the acceptor of perſons, nor he dothe not iudge,
<pb facs="tcp:4760:8"/>
and eſteme men after outwarde face, and outwarde apperaunce, but after the inwarde affeccyon of the mynde, and pureneſſe of herte. Iudas by interpretacyon ſygnyfyeth confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyon or knowledge. It beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth vs to be Iudas, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſaie as to knowe and confeſſe Ieſus Chriſte, and hym crucifyed only oure redemer, Iuſtify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and Sauyor. Yf we beleue Chriſt to be our only Iuſtifyer, then wyl we not beleue our workes to iuſtifye vs or able to pourge vs from our ſynne, nor yet the Popes bullys, Pardons or any indulgencis graunted by Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes, Cardinalles, or Byſſhoppes, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed bedes, or meſſys ad Scala ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly may purge vs from ſynne, or take awaye oure ſynne, by ſtrength of the worke it ſelfe. For if remiſſyon of ſyn myght be had by the ſtrenght of any worke in it ſelfe, then Chriſte dyed in vayne, then his death is not to vs
<pb facs="tcp:4760:8"/>
ſo precyouſe, but ſome warke myght haue bene to vs as precyouſe as his death, whiche thing God forbid that any man ſhulde ſay or yet thynke.</p>
            <p>The ſeruaunt of Ieſus Chriſte. In theſe he ſheweth his office or dew<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie ſayenge that he is a ſeruaunte. He calleth hym ſelfe not a Lorde, a may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, a Kynge, an Emperour, to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue Kinges and Prynces, and that Kynges ſhulde knele &amp; kyſſe his fete but he calleth hym a ſeruaunt: not of euery one, as of men, to pleſe men, to be a man pleaſer and to preache theſe thynges that ſhulde pleaſe men, and to plaie the legate of men of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde But he calleth hymſelfe the ſeruaunt of God, and his offyce or duety to be to pleaſe God, to confeſſe Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus openly and playnly euery where and in all places, to playe the Legate of Chriſte Ieſus, to preache Goddes wordes boldely withoute all feare,
<pb facs="tcp:4760:9"/>
without all drede amonge all men. The Apoſtell here in theſe wordes he checketh, and rebuketh theſe that be aſſhamed to confeſſe them ſelues to be the ſeruauntes of God, that be aſſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to preathe Goddes worde purely and ſyncerly, that for feare of men, for hynderaunce of lucre or aduauntage wyll not openly confeſſe the trueth of Goddes goſpel, nor yet ſuffer other to do it, nor be wyllynge that other ſhal ſhewe it for feare of decay of their ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noure, promocyon, dignytie, frende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyppe of men, lucre or aduauntage. Also the Apoſtell checketh all theſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wyll not preache Goddes worde, but mannes tradicyons, mannes phanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyes, and dremes, mannes learning, and mans inuencyons, and that for the worde of God, and in the ſtede of the worde of God. Theſe be they that be men pleaſers, and ſtudyes rather to pleaſe man then GOD. But
<pb facs="tcp:4760:9"/>
ſuche be not the ſeruauntes of God, but the ſeruauntes of men, whome they ſtudye to pleaſe. Theſe be not the ſeruauntes of Ieſus Chriſte, nor his trewe Apoſtles, althoughe in wordes ſumtymes they may call them ſelues the ſeruauntes of Chriſt and his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, yet they be not the ſeruauntes of Chriſte, nor his Apoſtells, but they be falſe Apoſtelles, as Iudas Iſcaryoth was, and with hym are to be nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and reckenned, and with hym ſhal haue their rewarde in hell.</p>
            <p>The brother of Iames. Theſe wordes be added les any man ſhulde thynke Iudas Iſcaryoth the betrayer of Chriſt Ieſus to be the author of this pyſtell, and for to knowe Iudas Tha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deus whiche was the author of this e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyſtel from Iudas y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> betraier of Chriſt Then it is not lyke, Yee let no man thynke that Iudas put in theſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des for any vayne glorye, or any ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunſynge
<pb facs="tcp:4760:10"/>
of hym ſelfe that he was the brother of Chriſt or his kynſman, all ſuche carnall affeceyon was farre from his mynde.</p>
            <div n="1" type="verse">
               <head>To thoſe that be called / and in god the father halowed and by Ieſus Chriſt preſerued.</head>
               <p>Nowe ſheweth the Apoſtell vnto whome this Epiſtell was wrytten, it was written not onely to the Iewes, but alſo to the Gentyls, to all men be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leuinge in Chriſte it was written in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differently, to all that be called eyther by ſecret and preuy inſpiracyon, or by open preachynge of the worde of God to beleue in Chriſte Ieſus, whiche in God the father be ſanctifyed. But theare is many that is ſanctifyed, or bleſſed but not of God, but of man, as of Popes, cardynalles, byſſhops, Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bottes, whiche weryth their myters, and other tymes doth blyſſe &amp; l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tify
<pb facs="tcp:4760:10"/>
men, but peraduenture the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e that be thus bleſſed of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be curſid of god. Of ſuche that be only ſancrifyed of men, &amp; not of God Iudas doth not here ſpeke but ofſoche as be ſanctifyed of GOD wheder they be curſed or bleſſed of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and ſurely theſe be ſanctyfyed. Some peraduenture wyll aſke who be they that be bleſſed and ſanctifyed of God, trewely all they whome Chriſte hath ſanctyfyed in his bloude, &amp; waſſheth theyr ſynnes in his bloode that hath faith and doth beleue their ſynnes on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be taken awaye by Chriſte, &amp; his blode ſhed for their remiſſyon of ſyns and whithe wyll beleue ſurely tyll they dye theſe be they whiche be truly halowed &amp; ſanctified in god the father and theſe be holy and bleſſed, whether men do bleſſe them or turſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, other there be y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be ſanctifyed as of men, as of the pope, of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cardynals, of byſhops or of Abbottes, but theſe be not hooly
<pb facs="tcp:4760:11"/>
nor bleſſed, excepte that Chriſte hath ſanctifyed them in his blode, and haue remyſſyon of theyr ſynnes by Ieſus Chriſte, whiche thinge they beleue ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely, or elles they be not ſanctifyed of God nor bleſſed, be they neuer ſo often tymes bleſſed of the Popes holy hande and all his thre Croſſes, with all the myters of his Cardydnalles &amp;, byſſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes. Oftimes it fortuneth god to curſe theym whome men do blyſſe, and the contrary thoſe to be bleſſed of GOD who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> men do curſe, as god doth ſpeake by his Prophet, ſayenge I wyll blyſſe your curſynges, and contrary I wyll curſe youre bleſſynges.</p>
               <p>For as moche as this Apoſtell Iudas wrote to them that were aliue whom he ſayde was ſanctifyed it is euidente this worde ſanctum or ſanctifycatum in ſcripture for the moſt parte to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge for hooly men that lyueth, that is to ſay for good &amp; faythfull men and
<pb facs="tcp:4760:11"/>
not onely for thoſe that be departed hence, and called vnto the number of hooly ſainctes in heauen, whome the churche of Rome hath canonyzat and only calleth ſainctes. They that after that waies only wyll take this worde ſanctumin holy ſcripture they erre fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the trueth, and giueth greate occaſyon of impiete to other and maketh many to erre in takynge of ſcrypture in the trewe ſence. Theſe men bringe great darknes to ſcripture, they make ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture darke, and wyll not ſuffer hooly ſcripture to be ryght vnderſtande, but do alyenat and plucke awaye from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true and proper ſence of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ghoſt the faythfull Chriſten reader whiche deſyreth to haue the true intellygence of ſcripture. Howe can they truely vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derſtande ſaint Paules piſtell which he wrote to the ſamctes that were at Rome, yf they wyll take this worde ſanctum or ſancti for ſainctes that be
<pb facs="tcp:4760:12"/>
departed. Sainet Paull in a maner wrote all his epyſteles to ſainctes as it doth appere in a maner throughe al his epyſtels in the beginnynge. How can it be but theſe men whiche taketh ſayntes only for them that be departed but they muſt nedes counte Saincte Paule for an ideot foole which wrote his epyſtelles to the Sainctes depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted whiche coulde not reade them, nor yet when they were redde culde heare them, or vnderſtande theym, or any fruyte or profyte take of them, or any thyng gather of them to obtayne true fayth, or to faſſyon good manners, to fle ſynne and iniquytie, for Sainctes that be departed be paſſed the ſtate of this preſent lyfe. It is euydent ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that Sainct Paule calleth good and faythfull chriſten men lyuing af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the lawe of GOD in fayth and in charyte. Saintes althoughe they lyue in this preſente lyfe, or howe coulde
<pb facs="tcp:4760:12"/>
any man truely vnderſtande this py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtell of Iude whiche Iudas dedycated to ſainctes, yf ſainctes were only ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for ſainctes departed this lyfe. Iu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>das thadeus wrote to them that were a lyue, wherfore it is manyfeſt thys worde ſainctes muſt be taken in holy ſcripture as well for Sainctes being a liue in this preſent lyfe as for ſainc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes that be departed. For ſainctes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge a lyue taketh ſaincte Paule this worde ſayntes oftymes as it appereth Rom. xv. Ephe. pri. Colocen. pri. and ofter it is ſo taken, then other wayes.</p>
               <p>Becauſe many hath not taken this worde ſaynctes in ſcrypture for good men lyuynge, but only for hooly men departed. And alſo becauſe ſaint Paul deſyreth oftymes the prayers of ſainc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes for hym as is written. Roma. xv. and ſainctes they toke only for ſainc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes departed, ſeinge there is no ſcryp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to perſwade vs to pray to ſaintes
<pb facs="tcp:4760:13"/>
departed, no co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of god leſſe in holy ſcripture that I do remember no promyſe that we ſhal optayne our peticyon yf we praye to the ſainctes, but all ſcrypture doth perſwade, Ye commaunde to praye to God whiche is the gyuer of all that is good, he byd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth aſke of hym and we ſhall haue. Iacobi primo. Math. ſepti. To praye to God perſwadeth all holy ſcripture, Math. vi. and alſo promyſeth that we ſhall not aſke in vayne, but that we ſhall optayne our peticyon yf we aſke as we ſhulde do and in fayth nothing douttynge but we ſhall optayne that we deſyre, yf it be to the glory of God and for our profite to receyue it. How prayenge to Sainttes dyd come vp, I haue ſhewed myne opynyon. To praye vnto Sainctes that they maye praye with vs vnto GOD I thynke it not euell. I thynke it a very good and laudable cuſtome, and maye be
<pb facs="tcp:4760:13"/>
well vſed, ſo that men make not ſayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes theyr patrones and gyuers of that thynge that they deſyre, as many hath done in tymes paſt, and put more truſt more co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fidence in a ſaynt, then in god: therfore they beynge in any peryll or icopardye, wolde renne to this image or y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> image o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſuche a ſaint before god. Thus the ignorant people hath prefer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red the ſayntes before god: &amp; put more truſt, more co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fidence, more helpe, more ſuccour in a ſaynt then in god: yea I fere me that many hath put their truſt helpe and ſuccour in an image made of ſtone or of wode by mans hande, &amp; done great reuerence &amp; honour to the image, beleuynge great vertue, great holynes to be in that image aboue o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther images: and therfore that image muſt haue a veluer cote hanged all w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> brouches of ſyluer, and moche ſyluer hanged aboute it &amp; on it, with moche lyght before it, and alwayes candels
<pb facs="tcp:4760:14"/>
burnynge before that image, whiche candle may neuer go forth, nor be put out: that light before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> image to be put forth it is a great faut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>and ſome thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth that the image wolde take a ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geaunce on ſuche y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhuld do it, whiche thynge I wolde no man ſhulde do in contemnynge the ſaynt whoſe image there is, but I wolde haue this euyl o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pynyon out of the ſymple harte, that they ſhuld eſteme images after the va<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lowe as they be, and put no more ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynes in one image then in an other, no more vertue in one than in an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. It holdeth the ſymple people in great blyndnes, and maketh them to put great truſt, great holynes in ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, becauſe one image is called our lady of grace, an other our lady of py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye, an other our lady of comforte or ſuccour: the holy rode of ſuche a place and ſuche a place. Theſe meanes ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the people to eſteme theſe images
<pb facs="tcp:4760:14"/>
of great holynes and vertue, and that they may do moche for them, and that ſome images of our lady prayth to our lady of heuen for her petitioners: ſuche is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſimplenes of many ſimple people.</p>
               <p>¶ As touchynge images to be in the churche I was neuer of other opinion but I thought it were commendable &amp; expedient to haue them to bryng vs in remembrance of the vertuouſnes and holynes of the holy ſayntes, that we may take example of them to folowe theyr godlynes and holy vertues, as to folowe theym in fayth, in hope, in charitie, in makenes, in lowlynes, in pacience, in ſufferynge iniuryes and wronges, in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>temnyng the worlde &amp; the vayne pleaſures therof, in lokyng for the lyfe ioye &amp; blyſſe to come. After this facion ſcripture teacheth vsto re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membre holy ſayntes in many places as ſ. Paul ſheweth Heb. xiii. Reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber you the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whiche hath had rule ouer you
<pb facs="tcp:4760:15"/>
whiche hath ſpoken the worde of god vnto you, whoſe fayth you do folowe, remembrynge what was the ende of theyr good co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſation. So ſaynt Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. i. Pet. iii. bringes in Saray for an example, that women ſhulde be obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to theyr huſbandes, &amp; pleaſe theyr huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandes, and haue theyr huſbandes in reuerence, as Saray had Abraham in honour and reuerence. Saynt Peter brynges the exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of Saray to teache other women to folow the example of Saray: ſo be images ſet vp in the chur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ches to put vs in remembrance of the vertuouſnes of the ſaynctes, that we ſhulde take example to folowe them in goodnes and vertuouſnes, to ſtere vp our dull hartes and ſlowfull myndes to god &amp; to goodnes was images ſet vp in the churche, and not for honour nor worſhyp that ſhulde be done to the image, whiche is but a thynge made of wode or of ſtoue, or other ſuche like
<pb facs="tcp:4760:15"/>
matter, and no more holyer then is the matter it was made on. Of theſe you may gather the good vſe of images.</p>
               <q>To thoſe that was called and in god the father ſanctified, and by Ieſus Chryſt preſerued.</q>
               <p>Here it is ſhewed to whom this pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtell was dedicate and ſent, that is to ſaye, to all men and women renewed by the bloode of Chriſte, whom Ieſus Chriſt hath called of his only mercy &amp; grace: and not of the merytes, werkes and deſeruynges of men. Fyrſt he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led them, &amp; then he dyd ſanctifye them. Here be two thynges to be noted, firſt that Ieſus Chriſte calleth whome be wylleth, ſeconde thoſe that he calleth he ſanctifyeth them: he calleth men to hym of his onely mercy, &amp; not of theyr merites, nor yet of their worthynes of theyr workes. God calleth ſomtyme in wardly by inwarde inſpiration, as
<pb facs="tcp:4760:16"/>
he dyd call ſaynt Paule Acto<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abrum"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>rum</ex>
                  </expan> ix. and many other prophetes. Somtymes he calleth in wardly in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hart, &amp; outward<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly by preaching of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> goſpel, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which they gyue credence y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be called. Chryſt calleth not after the pleaſure of man, but after the wyll &amp; pleaſure of god, &amp; when god wyll, &amp; not when man wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth, whom god pleaſeth to call, &amp; not whom man iudgeth worthy to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, nor yet when ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thynkes mete to be called, but when god thynkes and knoweth men apte and redy to come when they be called. By the whiche ſayinge many reaſons be taken away of the callynge after the wyll of man, by the merites of men, and when men iudgeth men to be apte and redy to the herynge of the goſpel, and wyll gyue credence to it.</p>
               <p>And although god onely doth call, &amp; when he wil without any indeuering or worke of man, yet oftimes &amp; for the
<pb facs="tcp:4760:16"/>
moſt parte he vſeth certayne meanes, as by prechynge of the goſpell, and by herynge of it preached, as he gyueth other gyftes by meanes, as lernynge by ſtudy, ryches by labour, wyſedome by experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, fayth by the goſpell prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched: ſo he calleth men to hym by prea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chynge of goddes worde, whiche they beleue that be called, and after it doth lyue a lyfe pure and clene in all inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency of lyuynge. God knoweth who be his, and thoſe he calleth to hym in tyme prefixed, and whan he knoweth theym mooſt apte to folowe theyr cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge. Here you may ſe the cauſe why god wolde not haue his goſpell at the fyrſt preached to the iewes &amp; to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyles, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in all tymes: it was becauſe he dyd ſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> then not apt to receyue it, nor yet apte to beleue it, therfore y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſhuld auoyde more payn god dyd hyde fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them his goſpell, &amp; when he dyd ſe them apt to receyue &amp; beleue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpell
<pb facs="tcp:4760:17"/>
he made the goſpell to be preached to the ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tyles, &amp; they beleued it, &amp; was ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued as many as was ordeyned to life.</p>
               <p>The order that god vſeth mooſt co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly to theym that ſhall be ſaued, it may here be gathered of the apoſtell Iude. Fyrſt he ſayth they be called, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly they be ſanctified in god the fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther, thyrdly they be ſaued by Ieſus Chriſt through his worde &amp; obedience to do theſe thynges gladly &amp; frely, that the worde of god teacheth them. This thyng ſaynt Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> teſtifieth Ioh. xvii. ſaying. Father I haue ſhewed thy na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me to men, whom thou haſt gyuen to me of the worlde: they were thyne, &amp; to me thou haſt gyuen them, &amp; they haue kept thy worde. Now truly they haue knowen, that al thinges whiche thou haſt gyuen to me was of the: for the wordes whiche thou dyd gyue me, I dyd gyue to them, and they haue recey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued them, &amp; they haue knowen truely,
<pb facs="tcp:4760:17"/>
that from the I haue gone, and tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thou ſent me. Here we may lerne the meane whiche God vſeth towardes them that ſhal be ſaued, although god only ſaue vs by hym ſelfe, by Ieſus Chriſte, and of his mere mercye and grace, yet he vſeth a meane wherby he bryngeth men to ſaluacyon, that is to ſaye by the worde of God preached and giuyng credence toyc, workyng after it, wherfore yf the worde of God be not preached nor had amonge vs, it is a greate token that we be not in the fauoure of God nor of his elected people to ſaluacyon. Alſo yf we in oure ſelues do perceyue no deſyre, no loue to the worde of God, but not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard it, eſteme it at lytell valu, thinke other thynges more precyouſe then it or thynke it folyſhnes, or as a vayne thynge. Then it is a token that theſe that thynke ſo they be none of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God, nor yet in the fauoure of
<pb facs="tcp:4760:18"/>
god as longe as they ſhall thynke ſo of theſe tokennes and ſygnes euerye one in hym ſelfe maye ſone perceyue whether he is in the fauoure of god or no. In that he hath a deſyre or a loue to goddes worde to heare it, to rede it, beleue it, to worke after it, to eſteme it aboue all worldely thynges. &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="verse">
               <head>Mercy be to you and peas / and charyte maye be multiplyed.</head>
               <p>In this ſalutacyon what thynge Saincte Iude deſyreth and wyſſheth to them to whome he wryteth, here it is ſhewed. He deſyreth that god wold encreaſe and multiplye hys gyftes in them, and ſpecyally gyue them mercy peace and charyte with hym, whiche thre gyftes be very neceſſarye for eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye Chryſtyan man and woman, as lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge as they ſhall lyue in this worlde The Apoſtell here teacheth vs what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hynge we ſhulde deſyre one vnto an
<pb facs="tcp:4760:18"/>
other, that is to ſaye the gyftes of god to be entreaſed and multyplyed amon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geſte vs, and in all men. From thys holſome councell of the Apoſtell Iude far be theſe men and women whiche do not deſyre nor wyſſhe good thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges vnto theyr neyghboures or other men, but deſyreth vengeaunce, euell chaunce, death of their neyghboure, or euell fortune to chaunce vnto theyre neyghboure or neyghboures cattell, or goodes, which doth curſe or banne theyr neighboures, deſyringe GOD to take a vengeaunce vpon theym, or to ſende ſum ſodeyne ſykneſſe, or dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe vpon theym, as the peſtylence, the fraunche pockes, the fallynge ſyck<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes or ſoche lyke. Thoſe men folowe not the councell of the Apoſtell in this place. Let therfore al ſuch euel perſons that folowe not the councel of the apo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtell leue their euell &amp; deuellyſhe affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon &amp; deſyre whiche bringeth euetla
<pb facs="tcp:4760:19"/>
ſting death, yf it be not left and for ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyn with repentau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce before deth, and folowe the holſome counſell of ſainct Iude, whiche deſyreth mercye, peace, and charyte to be multiplyed to euery one.</p>
               <p>Fyrſt he deſyreth to them the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cye of God, that it wolde pleaſe God to geue theym his mercye and grace, that they myght repent them of theyr olde vyces and ſynnes, and vtterly forſake theym, and haue a newe lyfe in Chriſte Iuſus, whiche thynge no man can do withoute the mercye and grace of god, therfore mercy and grace is firſt of all to be deſyred. Secundly he deſyreth Peace betwene men and God in mennes conſeyences, whiche Peace and quyetneſſe in conſcyence euell men hath not, for to euell men is no peace with God in their conſey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ences, as the Prophet ſayth, but euell men hateth god alway and feare hym
<pb facs="tcp:4760:19"/>
fore leſt he ſhulde punyſſhe them. For they counte god as a ſtrayte iudge or a cruell tormentoure that wyll ſuffer no faulte vnponyſſhed, but wyll ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremely punyſhe euery faulte, or treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pace done agaynſt him. The euel ſom tymes doth abſtayne from wyees and ſynnes, but not for loue of GOD, or of iuſtyce, but for feare of payne, or for hope of reward of men or fauor of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> The euell ſomtymes hath peace out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardely, as with men and with the worlde, but in wardly in their conſcy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence they lacke peace and quyetneſſe. In their herte they haue GOD as on wrath with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, their conſeyence byte them and troubleth them ſore, day nor nyght they be not quyet in conſcience but euer when they remember God, they feare payne, &amp; puniſhment. This conſyderynge Iude he deſyreth to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> peace in me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes conſciences with god whiche peace only hath gyuen men y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4760:20"/>
be inſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yfyed by faythe, wytneſſynge ſ. Paule. Ro. v. we iuſtifyed by fayth haue peace with God, whether they haue peace with the worlde, and men of the worlde or no, good men that be iuſtifyed by faith haue peas with god in wardly in their conſcience. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he deſyreth charyce, that they ſhulde be charytable and louing one to an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, knyt to gether in mutuall loue, one loayng an other hertely, &amp; ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge their loue by mutuall workes, and dedes, and that theyr loue ſhulde be onely for goddes cauſe, but not for no carnall lucre, or aduauntage, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noure, or any carnall cauſe. Thus in this ſalutacion we be taught what chriſten men ſhulde deſyre and wyſhe one to an other, that is to ſaye, mercye peace, and charyte of God, as the apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtell teacheth vs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="verse">
               <head>Beloued when I gaue all dily<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gence to wryte vnto you of the
<pb facs="tcp:4760:20"/>
commen helth / it was nedefull for me to wryte vnto you, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horte you that ye ſhuld continu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ally labour in the fayth which was ones gyuen vnto ſayntes.</head>
               <p>Nowe beginneth the narracyon, &amp; ſheweth the cauſe of the pyſtel ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge alſo what a greate deſyre wyll &amp; minde he had to profyte them, ye what care and thought he had for their helth ſpecially for theſe thynges y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> pertay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to their euerlaſtyng helth he had ſo gret a deſyre y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he could not refrayn but he muſt nedes wryte to theym ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng no les care for them the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for hym<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelfe perceiuing them to be in gret ieo perdy &amp; parell, by the craſte and falſed of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> falſe prophetes. Therfore Iudas perceyuinge theſe perils to aproche to chriſtians, &amp; moued by brotherly cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite he colde not te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>per hym from wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to ſhewe chryſten men of their pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relles,
<pb facs="tcp:4760:21"/>
and alſo to exhorte them that they wolde not ceaſe to walke in a pu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re and ſyncere fayth and loue whiche they had hearde preached and had ler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of the true Apoſtels of god. And alſo he deſyreth them to take heede of falſe Prophetes, whiche alwaye dyd ſtudy to brynge the true Chriſtyanes from the trewe fayth whiche they had receaued. Here we maye learne what ſtudy and deſyre it becommeth euerye one of vs to haue towardes an other, that we maye profyte other. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with all dylygence and ſtudye ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge, late vs exhorte other to walke in the treweth truely receaued, leſſe they ſhulde ware ſloggeſſhe by neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lygence, or ſlouthfulneſſe. Thirde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that they maye auoyde the parelles that be lyke for to enſue by ſlouthful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, or negligence, or by ignoraunce yf they be not monyſſhed ſpecyally, it becommeth for to monyſſhe to auoyde
<pb facs="tcp:4760:21"/>
parelles, when that parell of Soule doth appere. Thus it beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth euery man to care for an other, &amp; to mony ſhe an other o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iepardy y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> may enſu, both in worde &amp; alſo in writing, &amp; this care it may not be litel, but it muſt be gret w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al labour &amp; dilyge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to profit other as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple to be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in this place of Iude.</p>
               <q>Of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon helthe.</q>
               <p>For what thynge Iude laboureth ſo diligently to wryte to them here he ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>preſſeth, ſaying it was for the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon helthe. He calleth it the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon helthe becauſe he cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted their helth his helth ſuche was his loue towardes them, that he was no other wayes affected towardes them then towardes hym<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelfe countyng y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſame euyll to chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to hym ſelfe, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhulde chaunce to them by the crafte and ſuttiltie of falſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes, gyuyng vs example lykewiſe one to be affected towardes an other, as he was to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to whom he wroce,
<pb facs="tcp:4760:22"/>
and alſo as me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bres of one body be one to an other. This ſaying of Iude doth checke all them whiche be not careful for theyr neyghbours, nor for other be-ſydes them ſelfes, which care not what become of other, ſo they be well them<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelues. Alſo it ſharpely reproueth all them which care nothynge at all, nor nothynge dothe ſtudy howe they may profyte other, whiche paſſe nothynge at all what become of other, whether they lyue or dye, be ſycke or in helthe, be gladde or be ſory. Yea this ſermon of Iude moche more condempneth all thoſe that ſtudy to do hurte &amp; damage to other, or any maner of iniurye or wronge in worde or in dede.</p>
               <q>It was nedeful for me to write vnto you.</q>
               <p>As who ſhulde ſaye, I ſe it is ſo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for you y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I coulde not refrayne but I muſt nedes wryte vnto you, my
<pb facs="tcp:4760:22"/>
charite ſo compelleth me, perceyuynge it to be moche for your profyte, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horte you to go forwarde in that true faythe receyued, and to profyte in the ſame, and to encreaſe it dayly more &amp; more. And that you ſhuld not ſhrynke one heare brede from that true faythe whiche you haue receyued, and which was gyuen vnto the ſaynctes of god by preachynge of the goſpell, as ſaynt Paule ſayth Rom<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. x. Fayth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth of herynge, herynge veryly by the worde of god.</p>
               <p>He exhorteth them that they ſhulde continually labour in the fayth, or be helpers to the fayth (as Eraſmus tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation hath) whiche was ones gyuen to ſaynctes. Here be two thynges to be noted for oure lernynge. One is that he deſyreth theym to be helpers of the faythe, to the whiche men be helpers after this phraſe of ſcripture, whan they ſuffer not the fayth recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
<pb facs="tcp:4760:23"/>
to be weyke, feble or inconſtant, to be oppreſſed with deſyres or affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the fleſſhe or of the worlde, by the crafte or ſuttyltye of falſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes to be brought a waye from it, &amp; led in to a falſe belefe by falſe doctors whom the deuyll doth vſe as his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters to deceyue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſymple people vn lerned. Alſo ſcripture vſeth to cal men helpers of the fayth, when men do di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly watche that they be not decey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by the deuyll, nor by none of his miniſters, when they do labour with all force to make theyr fayth ſure and ſtronge, douttynge or haltynge in no part, but by al meanes ſtudyeth euery day to make their faith more ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger &amp; ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger by al maner of good warkes. The other thynge that was here to be noted, is that we ſhulde knowe fayth to be gyuen from aboue, for he deſireth them to be helpers to the ſayth, which was gyuen ones to ſayntes. Fayth is
<pb facs="tcp:4760:23"/>
the worke of god, &amp; it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth of god, as ſaynt Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſayth: this is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> warke of god, that you ſhulde beleue in hym. Saynt Paule wytneſſeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge Philip. i. Not onely it is gyuen to you that you ſhulde beleue in god, but alſo that you ſhulde ſuffer for his ſake. Of theſe two places of ſcripture it is euident ſayntes lyuynge or deed not to haue had fayth of them ſelfes, or of theyr owne myght &amp; power, but to haue receyued it of god, which gyueth fayth to whom he wil, &amp; when he wil, although ſaint Paul ſaith faith to com of the heryng of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word of god, which worde although many may here it, yet no man ſhall beleue but he to whom god gyueth fayth, and in whom god warketh fayth and beleue.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="verse">
               <head>For there are certayne craftely crepte in / of whiche it was wri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten a fore tyme vnto ſuch iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb facs="tcp:4760:24"/>
they are vngodly, &amp; turne the grace of our lorde god vnto wantonnes and denye god the onely lorde and our lorde Ieſus Chryſte.</head>
               <p>The apoſtel more at large ſheweth the cauſe of his admonition, whiche is to monyſhe them that they ſhuld arme them ſelfes with ſure armure &amp; defence to defende them agaynſt falſe, ꝓphetes and that they ſhulde in any wyſe take hede of them, leſt by the craft &amp; falſhere of pſeudapoſtels they ſhulde be decey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued &amp; alienated from the way of truth and from ſyncere doctryne of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpel. What maner of men were theſe pſeud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>apoſtels &amp; falſe doctours in the ſeconde piſtel of Peter ca. ii. it is ſhewed more abunda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly. And alſo here after ſhall be god wyllynge more playnly declared, how they haue come in, Iude here doth partly ſhew, ſaying they haue craftely
<pb facs="tcp:4760:24"/>
crepte in, not playnly preachynge the goſpel of god, but darkly &amp; colouryng it with great pretence of holines, mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting mans doctryne with gods word, teachyng mans doctryne, mans tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, dremes &amp; fantaſyes of men in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtede of gods worde, wyllynge &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwadyng as great fayth, as great au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorite to be gyuen to the traditions, &amp; writinges of men, as to gods wordes, gods holy <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>ceptes, but theſe be euyll &amp; falſe doctors of god deputed to iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that they ſhuld ſuffer paynes vn to the day of iudgement, and after that day y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſhulde ſuffer more greuous paynes in body &amp; ſoule togyder, ſeinge that now they ſuffer paynes &amp; punyſh me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes only in the ſoule, after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mynde of the doctors, &amp; ſhal ſuffer in the ſoule only paynes to the day of iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, &amp; after the daye of iudgement ſhall then ſuffer paynes and turmentes bothe in body &amp; ſoule, as the doctors doth ſay.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:4760:25"/>
               <q>They are vngodly and tourne the grace of our lorde god vnto wantonnes.</q>
               <p>They be ſo vngodly ſo vngracious that they turne al that we haue of god and of his grace to fulfyll and ſatiſfye theyr pleaſures, pluckyng to them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues haſty deſtruction &amp; eternall deth, they are ſo euyll &amp; myſcheuous full of all vnhappynes, that they turne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> free benefyte of god &amp; grace, by the whiche Chriſt hath delyuered vs from ſynne, deth, hell, deuyll, and eternal dampna<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion, and made vs innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes and free from all captiuitie of ſynne, and ſet vs in innocency &amp; holynes (whiche thing ſhuld moue vs to kepe innocency &amp; ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lynes) they turne this libertie of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryte wherby men be ſet to do all good thynges and no euyll, to do only thoſe thynges to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche the ſpirite of god moueth and exhorteth. Theſe vngodly
<pb facs="tcp:4760:25"/>
turne this liberty in to a carnall liber<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty in occation &amp; liberty to ſynne, &amp; gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth them ſelfe holly to wantonnes, ſo laſciuiouſnes, to vnclenlines, to baw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry, to fornication, to adultery, &amp; other many vices &amp; ſynnes, nor yet they are not ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent, but they denye their mai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſter whiche hath redemed them by his precious blode, they denye their maiſter not openly &amp; before al men &amp; playnly, but ſecretely in corners &amp; craf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ely they denye theyr maiſter. But when denye they thus theyr maiſter priuely and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly? Truly when they aſcribe their iuſtification, forgyuenes of ſynnes to any creature, or to any warke by the might and power of the warke, to any indulgence or pardon, to maſſes ad ſca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>la celi, to holy beades, to kyſſynge of images &amp; ſuche lyke, and not to Chriſt Ieſus and to his bloode ſhedde for vs to optayne vs remiſſion of ſynne, by whoſe bloode onely we were waſſhed vs in
<pb facs="tcp:4760:26"/>
from our ſynnes, as ſaynt Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſayth Apoc. 1. He hath waſhed vs i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his blode from our ſynnes. They denye the lord whiche aſcrybeth remiſſion of ſynnes to any other thynge then to Chryſte &amp; his blode, whiche thyng falſe, ꝓphetes dothe, denyenge theyr mayſter.</p>
               <q>They turne the grace of god to wantonnes.</q>
               <p>As who ſhulde ſay, they were called and redemed with the precious bloode of Chriſte Ieſus, that they ſhulde lyue in all innocency &amp; puritie of life, in all holynes &amp; godlynes. But they be tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated &amp; turned fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all innocency &amp; pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of lyfe, &amp; turned to all maliciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, wantonnes &amp; fylthines. They be tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſlated. q. d. they be all chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holynes to the whiche Chryſt dyd call them, &amp; by benefit dyd inuyte them but they be tranſlated from y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> holynes, &amp; be tranſlated after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maner of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Gala<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, of whom ſaint Paule co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>playneth
<pb facs="tcp:4760:26"/>
ſaying, I merueile that fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che hath called you by grace, you are ſo ſoone tranſlated in to an other goſpell whan there is none other: but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſome men there be y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> troubleth you, &amp; wolde inuerte the goſpel of Chriſt Gala. 1. as theſe of whom ſaynt Iude here co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, that they tranſlated the grace of god in to wantonnes, and they were vtterly tranſlated from all holynes, to the whiche Chriſt had called them: ſo I feare that we chriſtians be tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſlated from the doctryne of Chriſt, &amp; from the true fayth taught in it, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> byſſhop of Rome &amp; his lawes, by decrees, ſtatutes &amp; traditions of the churche of Rome, in to the forgetfulnes of goddes lawe, of goddes commaundement, in to other maners &amp; facions then goddes lawe doth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde or ſuffereth: yea we be farre tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſlated by the byſhop of Romes lawes amonges vs vſed and vſurped ſo longe, that many one doth thynke &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:4760:27"/>
hath thought y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> biſhop of Romes lawe to be gods lawe, &amp; to haue lyke autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> gods lawe, &amp; that it byndeth no leſſe than gods lawe: yea this lawe of the byſſhop of Rome hath brought vs ſo far out of frame, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſcarſe we thynke thoſe thynges ꝑteyne vnto vs whiche gods worde byddeth &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth vs. Therfore let vs be ſory for this tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation from Chryſte &amp; his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, &amp; be tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſlated agayne to Chryſt, that we may do thoſe thynges whiche Chriſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeth vs, that we &amp; our warkis may be acceptable before god.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="verse">
               <head>My mynde is therfore to put you in remembrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / for as mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che as ye ons knowe this / how that the lorde after that he had delyuered the people out of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gipte, deſtroyed theym whiche beleued not.</head>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4760:27"/>
Iude bryngeth in here, iii. era<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples of theſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> tranſgreſſed the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dement of god, &amp; was puniſhed for their ſynne to pluck back other fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſynne for feare of punyſhment, whiche our lorde wyll gyue to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wyll not ceſſe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſynne, puniſhment fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the begynnynge was euer <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>pared &amp; deputed for ſynners, as to good men a rewarde in ioy &amp; blyſſe. But although good me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath euer b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n rewarded, &amp; euyll men punyſſhed, yet there is a differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, good men hath ben &amp; ſhal be rewarded by life euerlaſtyng not of their merites, or for the worthy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of their workes, but only of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy &amp; goodnes of god. Euyll men hath ſuffered paynes &amp; punyſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for theyr iniquite &amp; ſynnes, &amp; becauſe they haue done euyll, therfore god of his iuſtyce hath punyſſhed them, and to refrayne other from ſynne for feare of punyſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment here.</p>
               <p>Iude bryngeth in thre examples, by
<pb facs="tcp:4760:28"/>
the whiche he ꝑſwadeth that god wyl punyſſhe ſynners that wyl not repent and leaue theyr ſynne. The firſt exam<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple is taken of the people of Iſraell brought out of Egypte from the great bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dage of Pharao, whiche oppreſſed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people of god with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tollerable paynes &amp; labours. Of the whiche people god at the laſte had mercy, and delyuered theym from theyr bondage, &amp; brought them ſauffe out of Egypte. But theſe people not beleuynge god hath kylled in the deſerte. Of the whiche, we may note the goodnes of god in his people whom he wold ſaue and delyuer from all bondage &amp; perylles. Seconde the vnkyndenes of theſe people not bele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge the promyſes of god, ſeing that god had done ſo moche for them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as to delyuer them from the bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage and cruelty of Pharao, aboue all mans expectation, and had punyſhed Pharao with all his adherentes with
<pb facs="tcp:4760:28"/>
great plages and punyſhmentes, and at the laſt drowned hym with all his hooſt in the reed ſee, and alſo had done for them, that they thought more then all this, had brought theym throughe the reed ſee as by the drye waye in to the deſerte, where he fedde them with meate ſente from heuen, that is to ſay, with ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>na, &amp; had gyuen them drynke out of the peter ſtone. At the laſt theſe people for all theſe thynges not bele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng goddes promyſes, but complay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge, grudgynge and murmurynge agaynſt god and againſt Moyſes, god hath punyſhed with deth in the deſert for theyr offences. Of the whiche we may ſurely perſwade vnto vs, yf god haue punyſſhed theſe people whom he loued ſo well, for whom he dyd ſo mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the, &amp; to whom he ſhewed ſuche bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fytes, yf god haue punyſhed them with deth as he dyd for their i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>credulite &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belefe &amp; their ſynnes: how moche more
<pb facs="tcp:4760:29"/>
is it euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that he wyl not ſuffer falſe apoſtels or other offendynge and bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge his lawes to be vnpunyſſhed. Therfore let all ſynners beware and repen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> betyme and leaue ſynne, for yf they do not, they may be ſure they ſhal n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> eſcape without punyſſhement.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="verse">
               <head>The aungels alſo whiche kept not theyr fyrſte eſtate / but lefte theyr owne habitation he hath reſerued in euerlaſting chaynes vnder darknes vnto iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the great daye.</head>
               <p>Now Iude bryngeth in the ſeconde example by the whiche he afrayeth ſyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ners fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſynne by feare of payne &amp; pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſhment. And this example is taken of au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gels created of god in a hye &amp; glo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rious nature, to whom ꝓfited nothing their excellenci of treatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for as moche as they dyd not kepe theyr innocency in which they were created in, but left
<pb facs="tcp:4760:29"/>
their innocencye, and dyd fall to iny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quytie and ſynne, pryde prycked them ſo greately, yf God this noble and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellente creature offendyng, I meane Angelles offendynge hath ponyſſhed and depryuat the heauenly lyght, and to euerlaſtyng darknes hath commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them, where they be kepte in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall chaynes in darknes, vnto the daye of iudgemente, and after euer to be ponyſhed yf god hath poniſhed An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelles offendynge, howe moche more other offendynge, he wyll ponyſſhe, whiche from theire ſynnes wyll not ceſſe.</p>
               <p>This ſaienge of Iude doth appere to ſhewe that the Angells was crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of God that they ſhulde lyue in all innocency and kepe their place in hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen deputed vnto them for their inha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bytacyon and dwellinge place, from the whiche they did fall by ſynne, and was caſte hedlynges in to this darke
<pb facs="tcp:4760:30"/>
ayre, bounde in chaynes of darknes, and they be kepte in a darke place, whiche is contayned from the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens aboue, vnto the lowe grounde, as Faber doch ſaye, and that vnto the daye of iudgement, and then they ſhal be giuen and commytted vnto the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall punyſſhemente of hell, euer there to be punyſſhed in paynes euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtynge.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="verse">
               <head>Euen as zodom and gomor, &amp; the Cities aboute them, which in lyke maner defyled them ſel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ues with fornicacyon, and fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed ſtraunge fleſſhe, are ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> forthe for an enſample, and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the vengeaunce of eternall fyre.</head>
               <p>The thyrde enſample is here put whiche is of zodomme, and gomor,
<pb facs="tcp:4760:30"/>
and other Cyties polluted in theyr fylthynes, therfore punyſſhed of God for their abhomynacy on and ſynnes, as for fornycacyon, adulterye, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clenlynes, ſynne agaynſte nature, fylthy pollucyonnes, and other ſuche lyke, with theſe ſynnes ſpecyally the Apoſtell ſayeth, they were polluted and defyled. And alſo that they followed ſtraunge fleſſhe, and not their owne fleſſhe they vſed, that is to ſaye, theire owne wyues in law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full matrymonye, but they folowed ſtraunge fleſſhe, that is to ſaye they dyd vſe other mennes wyues, may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, or virgynes immaculate, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther women, and alſo men vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, contrarye vnto nature. wyues vnto theyr lawfull houſebandes be not called ſtraunge Fleſſhe in the ſcrypture, but the proper Fleſſhe of their huſbandes, as appereth by ſaint Paule Epheſ. quinto. where ſaynct
<pb facs="tcp:4760:31"/>
Paule exhorteth men to loue theyre wyues as theyr owne bodyes, for he that loueth his wife he loueth him ſelf no man doth hate his owne bodye but he wyll noryſſhe and cheryſſhe it, as the LORDE doth his churche, and for this a man ſhall forſake his father and mother and ſhal be coupled to his wyfe and they ſhalbe two in one fleſh wherfore it is euydent that the fleſſhe of the wyfe to the huſbande is not cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led ſtraunge fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſhe, this fleſſhe God dyd gyue to the man as a lawfull re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medye for the infirmyte of the fleſſhe, that by thys lawfull remedye had in matrimony matrimony all adultery, &amp; fornycacy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhulde be eſchued &amp; vtterly eriled.</p>
               <p>Fordermore in that the Apoſtell ſayth theſe ſodomytes to haue folow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſtraunge fleſhe. He doth appere to note theym of vnclenlynes and ſum fylthynes agaynſt nature by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which they were polluted as apperith gene.
<pb facs="tcp:4760:31"/>
xix. and ſainct Paul. Ro. i. But vnto what purpoſe be theſe thre exſamples brought in here of iude? Truly to fere men from ſynne, leſſe they ſuffer lyke payns with them: whome god puniſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed for their ſynnes, whiche paynes are more greuouſe, they ſhall not eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kape whiche wyll not leue theyr ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and repent, but continue ſtyll in ſynne and prouoke other vnto ſynne whether it be by their euell doctryne or euell example,</p>
               <q>Suffre the paine of euerlaſting fyre.</q>
               <p>Theſe wordes of the apoſtle ſhew<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth playnly thoſe ſynners ſpoken of before to ſuffre paynes of euerlaſtyng fyre, whereſoeuer they be other in hel or in the aer, it maketh no mater of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> place where they be it is certayn that they ſuffre great paynes and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes in euerlaſtynge fyre. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let euerye man beware to ſynne,
<pb facs="tcp:4760:32"/>
lecſte they ſuffre lyke paynes in fyre, worlde without ende as theſe doth to the whiche paines they ſhall be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mytted by the iuſtyce of god that wyl not ceaſe from ſynne, and from brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge gods commaundement.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="verse">
               <head>Lykewyſe theſe dremers defile the fleſſhe / deſpyſe rulers / and ſpeake euell of them that are in authoritie.</head>
               <p>Iudas here teacheth certayne pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertes of them whom he wylleth chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſten men to flee and eſchue, he calleth them dremers or mocked in dremes, and deluded, as one that dremeth, is deluded by certayne vayne fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſyes, or imagynacyons whiche he doth appeare to ſee or heare, as he that dremeth thynkes ſumtyme he heareth or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eith that thynge, whiche he nother dyd heare nor ſee, or to be in a place
<pb facs="tcp:4760:32"/>
where he is not, or to haue theſe thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges that he hath not, ſomtymes to be gladde, ſometimes ladde, but when he wakes, he perceyuith his dreme to be a vayne thynge, of no certaynce of no trouth, of a deluſyon, he is aſhamed of his dreme: he wolde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no man ſhulde knowe it, he is aſhamed to ſhewe it to any man he is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>temneth it, and ſetteth it at nought, to theſe dremers Iude aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembleth pſeudapoſtelles falſe prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, preferrynge mennes lawes, and mennes tradycyons aboue God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des lawe, or makynge theym equall with Gods worde, or ſuch as preache or ſette vp mannes doctryne, in the ſteede of Goddes worde, theſe he aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembleth vnto dremers, and he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth them dremers, or deludyd by dre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, but it ſhall chaunce vnto theym at the laſt yf it ſhal pleaſe god to open their eyes from their dremes &amp; make theym awake, that they ſhall ſee that
<pb facs="tcp:4760:33"/>
they haue dremed and that they haue bene deluded by dremes, &amp; ſurely they ſhall perceyue theire dremes to haue bene folyſſhe &amp; vayne thynges of the whiche they maye be aſhamed of.</p>
               <p>Amongeſt theſe dremers, whome ſainct Iude doth ſpeake of, there hath ben ſome dremers deluded in dremes whiche hath dremed y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they had pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and authoritie of God to make for theire wyll and pleaſure what they lyft, and that thynge that they wolde ſhulde be takyn, as an artycle of the fayth, ye they dyd dreme that they had authorite to make articles of the faith Canons, and rules whiche ſhoulde iuſtyfye and ſanctifye men: that they had authoryte to gyue pardon and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence whiche coulde abſolue a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na et a culpa. i. whiche culde delyuer from payne and from ſynne, furder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more amonge theſe dremers ſum hath dremed that they had power to remit
<pb facs="tcp:4760:33"/>
ſynne, and to gyue. xl. dayes or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. C. dayes of pardon, or ſo many yeres or mo of pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for paynes due for ſynne, &amp; that as ofte as it pleaſed them. And this pardon they called the treaſure of the churche, whiche theſe dremers had in theyr handes to beſtowe where they pleaſed. And not onely they had this treaſure for them ſelues, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſhulde beſtowe it at theyr pleaſure, that they onely ſhulde gyue dayes and yeres of pardon, and remyt ſynne as ofte as it ſhulde pleaſe them: but alſo they had it for other creatures without life, as for a ſtocke, a ſtone, a pot, a maſer, a boll, as ſaynt Bedes boll, ſaynt Edmundes boll, that he that ſhuld drynke of theſe ſhulde haue. xl. dayes of pardon. Of theſe yf he ſhulde drynke tyll he were dronken, I ſuppoſe he ſhulde haue ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny dayes of pardon: ſo by lykely hode they wolde haue made dronkennes a vertue, a good thynge ſpecially yf any
<pb facs="tcp:4760:34"/>
man ſhulde drynke ſo he were dron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of that cup, maſer, boll, glaſſe, or horne halowed or pardonned by theſe dremers, how many yeres and dayes of pardon haue they graunted to theſe that come and viſyteth this image or that image, in ſuche a place or ſuche a place, to this crucifix or that crucifix, that is to ſay, to this ymage of Chryſt or that ymage, in this place more then in that place, feynynge god to do my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles becauſe of the holyneſſe of the images, and becauſe he wolde haue thoſe ymages honoured and worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped of men. What pardon hathe ben graunted to bedes halowed in ſuche a place, to laces, to knottes, to ſtaryons to Rome, to ſaynt Iames of Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poſtel, to ſaynct Thomas of Caunterburye, and in the yere of grace clere remyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyon a pena et a culpa. After this and ſuche lyke facions hath ben promyſed infynyte dayes and yeares of pardon
<pb facs="tcp:4760:34"/>
by theſe dremers. And if they haue not dremed, I reporte me vnto you that be awake, your dreme is gone, your eyes be open, you be no more in ſuche dre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, you be fully awaked thanked be god: and our mooſt ſoueraygne lorde lorde kynge Henry the eyght, whiche ſo entyerly loueth the veritye and the treweth of goddes goſpell, and wylleth it ſhall go forwardes, and hateth all ſuche dremers, dremyng of vanyties &amp; lyes, promyſyng ſuche thyngꝭ by crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, which only Chriſt dyd gyue vn to vs by his precious blode ſhed for vs on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe. If remiſſion of ſyn myght be gyuen by ſuche thynges, then dyed Chriſt i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vayn, then was Chriſt a foole to ſhede his blode to oprayne vs remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſynne, ſeing remiſſion of ſynne might haue com a more eaſier way tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by ſheding of Chriſtꝭ blode. We be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che beholdyng to theſe dremers y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they haue fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de a more eaſier way to opteyn
<pb facs="tcp:4760:35"/>
forgyuenes of ſynne then Chriſt dyd fynde, they be moche more wyſer then Chriſt, yf theyr inuention be true, this is theyr dreme: theſe that be awake do wel ynough perceyue theyr dremes to be vayne and vanite. Suche men not without a ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t cauſe be talled dre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers or deluded in dremes, becauſe we can not obteyne remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſynne but onely by Chriſt &amp; his bloode, ſayth ſaynt Paule Ephe. i. By Chriſt we be redemed, &amp; by his bloode we haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſynne. Iohe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s Apoca. i. He hath waſſhed vs from ſynnes in his bloode. If remyſſyon of ſynne be by Chriſtes bloode (as it is in dede) then it is not by the popes pardon, by indul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gence graunted by byſſhoppes to this thynge or that thynge, this cup, pot or boll, &amp; ſuche lyke. Awake therfore you dremers, yf any ſuch yet be in a dreme and know your dremes to be vayne &amp; lies, deceiue your ſelf &amp; other no lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger,
<pb facs="tcp:4760:35"/>
the nyght is gone, the daye is ſpronge vp, the ſonne ſhyneth all aboute, than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked be god.</p>
               <q>They defyle theyr fleſſhe.</q>
               <p>Who be they that defile their fleſſhe? <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eryly they which lyue al togyder in deyntynes &amp; pleaſure, gyuynge them ſelues to all voluptuous pleaſures of the fleſſhe, folowyng theyr fleſſhly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyres &amp; appetytes in all pleaſures that may be, without feare of god, or any ſhame of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde, caryng for nothing ſo they may ſatiſfye theyr carnall and beeſtly appetyte with voluptuouſnes and pleaſure, whiche thynge is theyr chefe deſyre &amp; wyl to fulfyl with plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure theyr fleſhly appetyte &amp; luſt.</p>
               <q>They deſpiſe rulers, and ſpeake euyll of them that be in autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rytye.</q>
               <p>Iude ſheweth more of their proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes, he ſayth they deſpyſe rulers, and
<pb facs="tcp:4760:36"/>
ſpeke euil of them that be in authorite. Here Iude reproucth &amp; checketh pſeud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>apoſtelles ſpecially for two vices, the one is that they pollute theyr fleſſhe, &amp; defyle it, lyuynge in voluptuouſnes &amp; pleaſure o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> theyr fleſſhe, the other is, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they deſpyſe rulers, that is to ſay, out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde powers ordeyned of god &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der god, they contemne, &amp; ſpeake euyll of comon rulers &amp; como<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> officers. But how deſpiſe they rulers? Truly when they deſpyſe, nothyng regardes empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, kynges, princis, lordes, comon myniſters of the comon welth, do not honour cheym &amp; reuerence to them as honour ſhuld be gyuen to hye powers vnder god, not obeyinge their lawful and iuſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dementes for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> comon welth, but eremptyng them ſelues fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the obedience of hie powers, and other alſo, chalengynge authoritie &amp; power aboue kynges &amp; princis, which autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie &amp; power aboue kynges &amp; princis
<pb facs="tcp:4760:36"/>
to be in this worlde ſaynt Paule dyd not knowe, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundynge euery man to be obedient to the hye powers, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge Rom<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. xiii. Let euery man be obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to the hye powers, he that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyſteth power, he reſyſteth the ordy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce of god, and he that reſiſteth the ordynaunce of god, he taketh to hym iudgement. Of ciuyle power ſaynct Paule dothe appere to ſpeake. Saynt Peter confirmeth the ſame thing, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. i. Petri. ii. Be you ſubiecte to all maner of creatures for god, whether it be the kynge as mooſt hyeſt, or it be dukes as of hym ſent to the punyſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of euyll men, or to the prayſe of good men. Conſyder gentyl reader, yf the eremptions grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted by the byſhop of Rome, by the whiche he hath eremp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted hym ſelfe &amp; many other relygyous howſes and relygyouſe men, as they call theym, and other ſpirituall men called from the obedyence of Cyuyle
<pb facs="tcp:4760:37"/>
rulers and powers, and wyll not be obedient to princis &amp; kynges, but be aboue them, &amp; haue princis &amp; kynges at theyr co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement, and they not obedient to the iuſt &amp; lawfull co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of princis, of kynges, and of other comon myniſters appoynted by kynges &amp; princis for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> comon welth. Loke gentyl reader yf this exemption come not of hym which contempneth rulers? Doth not this exemptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or pri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uilege exempte men from dewe obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to theyr ſuperyour powers: to whome ſaynt Paule Rom<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. xiii. ſaynt Peter. i. Petri. ii. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeth euery man to be obediente to ſuperyour po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers lette eueryman be obedient, be he religiouſe man, be he other, let no man thynke hym ſelfe to be exempted from the ſuperiour powers, as from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kynges grace &amp; his officers appointed by hym to be rulers in this realme, for any exemptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or priuilege grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted by
<pb facs="tcp:4760:37"/>
the byſſhoppe of Rome, whiche hath none ſuche authoryte by God graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that he maye exempte men from the authoritie and obedyence to their ſuperior powers, to whome Saincte Paule commaundeth euerye man to be obedyent. Roma. xiii. Hebreorum. xiii. Two vyces Iude notyth in thes pſeudapoſtles, the one that they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempne powers, the other that they ſpeake euell on them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="verse">
               <head>yet Mychaell the Archangell / when he ſtroue againſt the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell / and dyſputed about the bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dye of Moyſes durſte not geue raylyng ſentence / but ſayde the Lorde rebuke the.</head>
               <p>Iudas ſheweth theſe pſeudeapo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtells ſpeakyng euell of the hye pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers ordynated of God to be more bol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der then Mychaell the Archangell ſent to fyght againſt the deuel, whom
<pb facs="tcp:4760:38"/>
he durſt not curſe nor ſpeake euell of, yf the Archaungell of God Mychaell durſt not nor wolde not curſe the deuel nor ſpeke euel of him how moch more ſhulde not pſeudeapoſtells curſe good men and iuſt men put of god in autho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rite and in hye power, to whom euery man ſhulde gyue due obedyence, and be redy to do all lawfull commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, and not to reſyſt, to curſe, or to ſpeke euell of the hye powers to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> honour, reuerence, and obedience muſt be geuen accordynge to the mynde of ſaincte Paule. Roma. xiii. gyue vnto all men that is due. Gyue honoure to whome honoure is due, gyue feare to whome feare is due, gyue trybute and cuſtome to whome they be due. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>This place of Iude is a ſtraunge and rare place ſcarſe was founde in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other place in Scrypture, therfore this Epyſtell of Iude was reiected of the fathers, becauſe this place ſcarſe
<pb facs="tcp:4760:38"/>
was founde in any other place of ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture, that made mencyon that Michael dyd fyght with the deuell as touching the bodye of Moiſes, &amp; of what occaſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this contempcyon dyd ſpring vp, be cauſe ſcrypture co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendeth Moyſes ſo gretly, ſaieng no prophet to haue bene in Iſraell like to Moſes, as it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Num. xii. ſayth ſcrypture. Moyſes was meke aboue al them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> dwelled in the erth and a lytel after y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſaith, if any ſhalbe amonge you a prophet of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lorde in viſyon I wyll appere to hym, or by ſlepe I wyll ſpeke to him, but not ſuch is my ſeruaunt Moſes, which is moſt ſaythfulleſt in al my houſe. I do ſpeke to hym mouth by mouth openly, &amp; not by darke ſaienges &amp; figures, he dyd ſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> forde. &amp;c. Thus Moſes is hiely co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed in ſcripture, as apereth i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ero. xviii Iudas here peraduenture dyd take oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to ſpeke of Moſes of theſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des whiche is wrytten Deuterono. the laſte Chap. where it is playn that
<pb facs="tcp:4760:39"/>
after oure Lorde had ſhewed to Moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes the lande of promyſſyon promyſed vnto the fathers Abraham, Iſaac, and Iacob, and had ſayd that Moſes ſhulde not entre into that lande (&amp; that was for a myſtery that was hydde whiche ſainct Paul openeth hebreorum. vii. ſayenge that the lawe dyd brynge no man to perfeccyon that is to ſaye that the lawe coulde not iuſtifye ne bringe men to lyfe, of Moyſes it is wrytten the laſt of the Deut. that Moyſes dyd dye in the lande of moab, and was bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed and that no man dyd knowe his ſepulchre vnto this daye. The ſepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chre of Moyſes god wolde haue it vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>knowne, leſt the Iewes whiche coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted Moiſes for ſuche a great and a ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prophet ſhulde commyt ydolatrye, &amp; ſet vp idolatre vpon the ſepulchre of Moyſes, and worſhyppe Moyſes as God, for the Iewes was redy to ydo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latre, of this doth the contencyon ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere
<pb facs="tcp:4760:39"/>
to be ſprong vp bytwene Micha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell and the deuell, of the whiche con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tencyon Iudas here ſpeaketh of, the deuell wolde the bodye of Moyſes to haue bene ſhewed to the Iewes, that it myght haue bene to them an occaſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ydolatre, Michael wold it ſhuld not haue bene ſhewed vnto them, that they ſhulde haue had by it none occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyon of ydolatre, but that all ydolatre ſhulde be vtterly extincted and put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye, here you may learne the deſyre of the deuell whiche is to moue to ydo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>latre, to iniquite, and ſinne, good men they alwaye dyſſwade from ydolatry and ſynne, and taketh away all occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyon by the whiche paſſage maye be made to ydolatre and ſynne.</p>
               <p>Saynt Iohn apoca. xxii. doth ſpeake of a certeyn bataile bytwene Michael &amp; the deuyll. He ſayth there was made a great batayle in heuen. Michael ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaungell and his aungels dyd fyght
<pb facs="tcp:4760:40"/>
with a dragone, and the dragone and his angels dyd fyght agaynſte Micha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>el, but they haue not preuayled, nor yet no place of them was found any more in heuen, but the battel of whiche it is here ſpoken was of the bodye of Moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes whiche the deuell wolde haue had worſhypped y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Iewes myght haue committed idolatry on it, Michael dyd reſyſt hym, this is the meaning of this place after myne opynyon, yf it be the true meanynge of Iude take it, yf not take their mynde that bryngeth a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſence, and I my ſelfe wyl be glad to learne of better learned then I am (for I am of the leſt) y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true vnderſtandyng of this place, exceppe myne opynyon in good worth, till you heare a better.</p>
               <p>But to what purpoſe bringeth Iude in theſe, but that he wolde teche pſeud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>apoſtels ſhulde not ſpeake euell, curſe wyſſhe vnto the deuell, hyghe powers and ſuche as be put in authorytye vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb facs="tcp:4760:40"/>
GOD, vnto whome it becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth euerye man for to be obedient by the ordynaunce of GOD, and to haue theym in honoure and reuerence, and not to ſpeake euell of them. Yf My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaell the Archangell ſente of GOD as a comon minyſter, durſte not curſe or ſpeke euell of the deuell, what bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes is it pryuate men to curſe, to ſpeke euell of powers ordynated of GOD. Thys place of Iude dothe appeare to take awaye all euell ſpeakynge from pryuate men, of them that be ſet for co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon minyſters of the common welth. This place doth not inhybyte, ne let, but comon offycers maye rebuke euell doars and punyſſhe them, as it ſhal be thought moſt expedyent for the amend<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment of them that be euell, &amp; to auoyde more inconuenyence. Alſo this ſayeng of Iud doth take away al vengeance in word or in de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e from priuate men &amp; moniſhe them to remit al vengeaunce
<pb facs="tcp:4760:41"/>
to god, whiche wyl not ſuffre ſynners to eſcape vnpunyſſhed. Iudas vſeth here an argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the leſſe to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more after this maner. If aungels durſt not curſe euyl men, moche more men ſhuld not curſe or ſpeake euyll of good men, moche leſſe they ſhulde ſpeake euyll of good men beynge in authoritye.</p>
               <p>If our fore fathers dyd longe reiect this pyſtel of Iude for this place, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che in ſcripture ſcarſe i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any other place coulde be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, how moche more now ſhulde men reicet the ſayinges or wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynges that with holy ſcripture (I do not ſaye do not agre) but playnly doth repugne with ſcripture, &amp; farre diſſent fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſcripture: nor yet this doctryne doth not ſo far diſcorde from the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and ſo far contrary to the truthe: but they gete ſome patrones which w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all myght &amp; power wyll defende this doctryne as holy and good, as they do whiche ſet vp y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vſurped power of the
<pb facs="tcp:4760:41"/>
byſhop of Rome aboue kyngꝭ, princis and emperours, &amp; that by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ordynau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of god, as god &amp; his holy ſcripture dyd gyue to the byſſhop of Rome a ſecular power aboue kynges, princis and em<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perours here in this worlde, when it is euydent by ſcripture the byſſhop of Rome to haue none other power but at the pleaſure of princis, then in the mynyſtration of the worde of god, to preache goddes worde purely and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely, to reproue by it euyll men, as to do ſuche thynges as becommeth a preacher, a byſſhop, a miniſter of god<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> worde to do: other power dothe not Scripture attribute to the byſſhop of Rome, nor ſuffer hym to vſe. Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture wylleth hym to be a byſſhop, and to do the office of a byſſhop, and not to playe the prynce, the kynge, the empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, the lorde, and ſo forth, as Peter byddeth. i. Pet. v. Feade as moche as is in you the flocke of Chriſt, not play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge
<pb facs="tcp:4760:42"/>
the lorde in the cleare, that is to ſaye, in the elected of god, &amp; ſo forth.</p>
               <q>The lorde rebuke the.</q>
               <p>Mychaell wolde not rebuke the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyll, but remytted all vengeaunce to god, teachynge other in theyr proper cauſe to commyt vengeaunce to god, which ſhall iudge ryght, and punyſhe euyll doers. Therfore it is not conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyent that men ſhulde deſyre venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunce of euyll doers, ſeynge that god wyll punyſſhe malefactours and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge all iniuryes done to god, or to men, yf theſe malefactours wyll not repent and be ſory for theyr offences paſte. Theſe wordes of Iude do not appere to be of one that deſyreth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uengeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, but rather of hym that ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth what is to come of god, that the lorde wyll rebuke hym that ſtereth &amp; prouoketh men to euyll.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="verse">
               <pb facs="tcp:4760:42"/>
               <head>But theſe ſpeake euyll of theſe thynges whiche they knowe not. In to theſe thinges whiche they knowe naturally as bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes withoute reaſon they cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruppe them ſelues.</head>
               <p>Iude pueth theſe falſe doctors more bolder then aungels, for they dare take vpon them to curſe powers ordeyned of god, whiche thyng y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gels wolde not do in men. And leeſt theſe falſe do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors ſhuld ſay they had a iuſt cauſe to ſpeke euyl, or to curſe powers &amp; rulers and other not obeyenge their lawes &amp; preceptes. Iude ſayth they curſe not ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uyng a iuſt cauſe, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they do not vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derſtand theſe thynges for which they curſe &amp; ſpeke euyll, that is to ſay, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they do not vnderſtande a iuſt cauſe of their curſyng. And not only men Iude ſayth they curſe, but alſo other thyngꝭ which
<pb facs="tcp:4760:43"/>
they do not knowe that they curſe and ſpeke euyll of, as of doctryne &amp; wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyngꝭ whiche they neuer red nor herd, ye &amp; of ſuche doctrine as agreeth with Chriſtis doctryne &amp; lernyng of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtils: but theſe pſeudapoſtils ſpeke euil of it, whiche they knowe not, nor yet can gyue iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of it, for as moche as they neuer red it, nor herd it red. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongꝭ theſe men there be ſome ſo igno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rant of gods doctryne, that they haue wyſhed &amp; deſyred hartely of god, ſaynt Paules piſtels, yea the newe teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to be brent, ſaying all errours &amp; here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies to come out of ſai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Paules piſtels &amp; the newe teſtament, ſuche ſhamefull wordes &amp; deteſtable hath ſome doctors ſpoken, whiche wolde haue ben coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for lerned men, doctors in their ſci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ences, but as blynde as betils in gods lawe, and ignorant in goddes worde, and yet they were benefyced men, ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, ordynaryes, and heades of other,
<pb facs="tcp:4760:43"/>
ye of a hole cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey. O mercyful lorde what were the membres, when ſuche blynde beyardes were heades &amp; ordy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naryes, howe was the people of god fedde with goddes worde, when the heade wolde haue had goddes worde brente. Nothynge is more to the hurt and deſtruction of many ſoules in this realme, then is to haue one to be offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall, comyſarye and ordynarye vnder the byſſhop, that is ignorant in gods lawe and goddes worde, howe wyll he preache and teache hym ſelfe, what example wyll he gyue to other, what perſons, what viccars wyll he make of? Trewly ſuche as he is hym ſelfe, ignorant in goddes lawe, and ſuche as be lerned he wyll hate and deſpiſe, and they that wolde teache their flocke and feade with the holſome worde of god, theſe he wyll call heretykes, and accuſe them of hereſye, and impryſon them. Examples to many we haue in
<pb facs="tcp:4760:44"/>
this realme, I praye god amende it when his pleſure is. Suche ſhamefull wordes hath doctors in their facultye (as they call it) ſpoken, deſyrynge to haue had Sayncte Paules pyſtels, ye the newe teſtament brente. Of theyr ſayinges they haue ben nothing aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, nor yet of theyr ignoraunce nor blyndenes, but taken for ryght wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhypfull men, poſtes and pyllers of Chriſtis churche, theſe ignoraunt and blynde heades &amp; rulers of other howe coulde they preache goddes worde be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge thus affected? howe coulde they fauour thoſe that preached gods worde trewly and ſyncerely? Trewly they coulde not, this is the cauſe that trew preachcers of goddes worde in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alme be ſo euyll ſpoken on as they be, becauſe they exhorte al beneficed men to do theyr dewtye to preache goddes worde, to feade theyr flocke with the doctryne of god, that they myght ſaue
<pb facs="tcp:4760:44"/>
theyr ſoules in the daye of the lorde. But a great part of beneficed men no thyng regarde theyr dewty co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded them of god, nor the exhortation of the preachers, that is to feade theyr flocke with goddes worde, but neglygently deſpyſeth that office, and wyll neyther feade his flocke hym ſelfe, nor yet ſe or prouyde that they be fedde by other that can do it, yea they wyll ſpeke euyll of ſuche as preache goddes worde purely and ſincerely, &amp; make them to be endi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of hereſye, whiche preache goddes worde purely, which do feade y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people of god trewly with gods worde, ſuche is the affections of many perſons, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ars and curates, ſuche is theyr igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, ſuche is their blyndnes, god ſend them the lyght of his worde, that they may ſe it and vſe it to the helth of them and theyr flocke.</p>
               <p>Many there be that peraduenture thynketh it is ynough they do the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dement
<pb facs="tcp:4760:45"/>
of theyr ordynary, ſo that they neuer preche nor fede their flocke with gods worde, whiche men decey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth them ſelues yf they ſo thynke, for this wyll not excuſe theym before the hye iudge at the day of iudgement, as is euident Ezech. iii. xxxiiii. xxxiii. pri. Corinth. ix. Wo be to me ſayth ſaynct Paule yf I preache not. Iude here ſpeaketh in the neutre gendre, ſayinge that they dyd ſpeke euyll of theſe thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges whiche they dyd not knowe, by the whiche he vnderſtandethe many thynges. Here we may ſe what euyll it is to curſe thoſe thynges that men do not knowe, or that they haue ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther herde nor redde. To ſuche men ſaynt Ierome gyueth a good counſell in a pyſtell before Eſaie the prophete. He willeth that men ſhuld fyrſt reade, and then deſpyſe, leaſt they maye he thought not of a trewe iudgemente or knowlege, but of a preſumption,
<pb facs="tcp:4760:45"/>
of hatred to condempne thoſe thynges they knowe not yf men wolde folowe here ſaincte Hieromes counſell they wolde not be ſo redy to condempne as they be.</p>
               <q>whiche as beeſtes without rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon they corrupte them ſelues.</q>
               <p>Iude here ſayth they corrupte them ſelues naturally as brute beeſtes with oute reaſon, as who ſhulde ſaye they lyue in welth and pleaſure, and in ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfyenge the deſyre of their fleſhe, they paſſe brute beeſtes whiche be without reaſon whiche lyue after their nature, but theſe in the fylthynes of their fleſh they kepe not her meaſure nor meane, all together giuen vnto pleaſure of ea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tinge and drinkynge, and to ſatiſfy the other pleaſures of the body, wherfore they be worſe then brute beſtes which lyue after their nature.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11a" type="verse">
               <head>wo be vnto them / for they haue
<pb facs="tcp:4760:46"/>
folowed the way of Cayne.</head>
               <p>Here Iude no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eth theſe pſeudeapo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtels to be full of enuy, as Cayne was towardes his brother Abell whome he kylled. Cayn enuyed his brother abell becauſe his brothers ſacrifyce was bet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter or more iuſt then his. Geneſis. iiii. and therfore he dyd kyll him. So there be many y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> foloweth the waye of Cain whiche can not beare that other men, and other mennes workes ſhulde be preferred before theym, or theyre wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes. Here is to be noted, fyrſt Cayn an euell man to haue enuyed his brother Abel a good man. Secondly Cayne of enuy to haue perſecuted his brother be cauſe his brother was better then he, and his brothers workes preferred be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore hys. Thyrdely that it greueth euell men, other man, or other men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes workes, or oblacyons to be prefer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red before theym. Fourthely that two brethren of one man, and of one
<pb facs="tcp:4760:46"/>
woman, the one to haue bene good, and the other euell. Fyftely one bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to haue kylled an other of malice, enuy, and hatred. Syxtely learne en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy, and hatred to bryng murdoure, and man ſlaughter at the ende. Seuently learne that euell men allwayes enuy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth good men, perſecuteth theym with mortall hatred, without a cauſe, and at the laſte kylleth theym. And that this thynge is no newe thynge, here you maye ſee of Cayn, and Abell. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny there is that entre the way of Cayn and foloweth his foote ſteppes, in his enuy and malyce drowned, and theſe be called Caynys. Many there be nowe a dayes Caynys that enuyeth the true preachers of the Goſpell, but theſe ſhall haue a rewarde with Cayn to whom the apoſtell doth threate wo, that is to ſaye, euerlaſtynge woo and dampnacyon, that for feare of payne men ſhuld abſtayn from enuy &amp; hatred
<pb facs="tcp:4760:47"/>
The punyſſhemente taken iuſtely of Caine maye feare other from the enuy malyce, and hatred of Cayne. Iude ſay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>enge wo be to theſe men that goeth the waye of Cayn. He doth not deſyre wo to Caynis, but he ſheweth wo &amp; payne to come to them, whiche doth the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes of Cain, and fulfyll their enuy and malyce, by the death of an Innocent.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11b" type="verse">
               <head>And are ſpylte in the erroure of Balaam for lucre ſake.</head>
               <p>The apoſtell ſheweth woo to come to them whiche are ſpylte in the errour of Balaam, or polluted by ſuche coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſenes as Balaam was, he thretyth wo euerlaſtynge to theym, whiche for money, or for fylthy lucre ſake doethe theſe thynges that is not mete ne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient, whiche doth euer for their bel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly ſake, for hope of lucre or aduauntage After the example of Balaam, whiche for money wolde haue curſed the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb facs="tcp:4760:47"/>
bleſſed of god, more regardinge mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ney then the commaundement of god. Of this Balaam it is wrytten. Nu. xxii. xxiii. howe he was hyred of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ach to come and curſe the people of god, and howe he was content to do it for money, but god dyd not ſuffer hym but when he ſhulde haue curſed them, he dyd blyſſe them, whiche ſtory ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the noughtynes of man, and howe money wyl corrupt hym ſone, and that man can do no more then God wyll ſuffer hym. But there be nowe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny worſe then Balaam, whiche cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupte by money wolde only haue cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the people whome God dyd blyſſe. There be many worſe I feare me then Balaam, whiche not onely for money wolde curſe the people bleſſed of God, but alſo wolde begyle and deceyue, &amp; bringe them to erroure, to hereſyes, to ydolatrye for money. I praye you what Goddes or Goddeſſes haue they
<pb facs="tcp:4760:48"/>
ſet vp in many places to be worſhyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped to gette money with all of men? what worſhyp or veneracyon of ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges haue they ſucked oute of their fyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers for money. Images for to be a remembraunce of the holynes of ſain<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes I do approue, but to gette money with ymages I do not approue, yea what miracles ſay they hath ben done for the holyneſſe of the ymages, ſo be that they myght make theym more ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher by oblacions, ye who can tell half the wayes and meanes that they haue founde to get, ye to extort money from men, what by ymages, by pardons, by pylgrimages, by indulgenſes, by cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, by hallowynge of churches, churchyardes, belles, bokes, chalyces, veſtymentes, abbaſes, monaſteries, by relygyon of munkes, channons, fry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, preeſtes, byſſhoppes, cardynalles, and ſuche lyke, by prayers, bedys, pſalmes, maſſes, and many ſuche lyke,
<pb facs="tcp:4760:48"/>
and all inuenced for money, for with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oute money none of theſe conſecracy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or hallowynge is graunted what conſecracion maketh not the holy ſmel of money? no pardon, no indulgence, is graunted withoute money. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon came vp this comon verſe. Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ia romana non cupit ouem ſine lana, that is to ſaye the courte of Rome ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h not for the ſhepe without her fleſe or woll. Of ſuche marchaundyſe greate aduauntage, greate lucre hathe commen vnto the inuentours, to the Mayſters of this ſutteltye and craft, to them hath bene pleſaunde the ſmell of lucre, what matter ſo euer it were. Theſe be they that in a manner haue corrupted the hole worlde, in ſo moche that theſe thynges that be good &amp; iuſt can not come to paſſe without money. Therfore the Apoſtell threteth woo to them for they not onely are in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame decepcion with Balaam, but alſo they
<pb facs="tcp:4760:49"/>
are full of that deceiuablenes, therfore he ſayth they be ſpylte by this maner of deceyuing, that terme he vſeth to ſhew the abundaunce of their deceyt, for ther is no thynge they wolde not do for a vauntage, good ſmell to them always is a vauntage of luere or money, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny be nowe a dayes lyke vnto theym, whiche all ſhall haue a rewarde with them, that is to ſaye wo euerlaſtynge. Therfore forſake Balaams decepcion betyme, and be no more a Balaamyte, leſte wo com vpon you ſoner then you be ware.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11c" type="verse">
               <head>And are caſt a waye in the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of Core.</head>
               <p>Wo ſayth the Apoſtell ſhall come to theym, whiche be in the treaſon with Core, whiche dothe conſpyre agaynſte Moyſes, and Aaron, as Core and his companyons dyd. Of the coniuracion and conſpiracy ſtyred vp by Core and his companyons agaynſte Moyſes,
<pb facs="tcp:4760:49"/>
and Aaron, it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d Nu. xvi. how that Core not being content with his cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge and lotte wolde haue ben ruler to the people of god, whome Moyſes by the mighty power of god dyd bring out of Egypt. This Core perceyuyng he coulde not haue that rule that he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyred, he gathered a great nombre of people, and made a conſpiracy agaynſt Moyſes &amp; Aaron, &amp; ſo thought to haue kylled them, &amp; made hym ſelfe &amp; other whom he wolde rulers of that people, but god dyd not ſuffre hym to brynge to paſſe that he entended, but dyd caſt hym in his owne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ourne, god delyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red his ſeruauntes Moyſes &amp; Aaron, and ſhewed his myght and power a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt Core, Dathan, Abyron, &amp; theyr companyons, and made the earthe to open and ſwalowe Core, Dathan, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byron, &amp; all them that were of conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy with them. Here be ſome thinges to be noted. Fyrſt the maliciouſnes of
<pb facs="tcp:4760:50"/>
Core and of them whiche aſſented to hym. Seconde, that he was not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ent with his lot and callyng of god. Thyrde, that he dyd enuy Moyſes and Aaron, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> were elected of god to be ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of his people. Fourth, that he dyd gather other vnto hym, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thought his cauſe good, &amp; wolde take his parte, to put downe the rulers elected by god. Fift, that no man is ſo euyll nor haue ſo euyll a cauſe but there is ſome that wyll agre vnto hym, &amp; be wyllynge to helpe him to iuſtify his noughty cauſe. Sixte, Euyll agreeth ſoone to euyll, &amp; lyke wyll to lyke. Seue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>th, the punyſh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment of Core, Dathan, Abyron &amp; their companyons may monyſhe al other to to beware to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſpyre agaynſt Moyſes &amp; Aaron miniſters of god, the erth that ſwalowed them vp, may monyſhe all men y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſhal not murmure, grudge ne conſpyre agaynſt ſuche whom god hath put &amp; ſet in authoritie &amp; rule ouer
<pb facs="tcp:4760:50"/>
the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon peple. Therfore let al pſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> apoſtels and all other beware <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſt they murmure grudge or cauſe ſedition a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt the mynyſters of god agaynſt powers ordeyned of god, left it chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to them like vengeance as dyd to Core &amp; his companyons, by the whiche they haue peryſſhed. Le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne here how nyely they diſpleaſe god, that be not content with their lot, with theyr callyng, but wyl deſyre &amp; take an hyer honour then they be called to, Ye that wyll conſpire againſt powers ordyned of god, &amp; not be obedient to them, after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ordynau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of god Ro. xiii. The punyſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re &amp; his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s how highly they diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pieſed god doth ſhewe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> doth as Core did. O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Core you may rede y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtory Fru. xvi. &amp; there note mo thynges of hym.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12a" type="verse">
               <head>Theſe ar ſpottes which of your kyndnes feeſt togyder without fea. e feadynge them ſelues.</head>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4760:51"/>
Iude reproueth the iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the people towardes theſe pſeudapoſtels, of the ſymple people they be c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>unted to be the worſhyp, honour, and orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all charitie, of all vertue: but yf they be nerely loked on they are not that thyng that they be counted to be, they are not the honour nor the beauty but they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the very fyithynes it ſelfe, and the very ſpo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>es of whom co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth and ſpryngeth that thynge that befo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the hole face, the hole body. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore in that he ſayth that they be the ſpottes amonges your charytyes, as Eraſmus tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſlation hath, an other thynge he doth appere to ſaye, as who ſhulde ſay, they by craf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, ſuttelty, falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hede, hypocryſye and ſymulation hath goten of you great rycheſſe, great poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions, landes and tenementes, whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che you haue gyuen to theym of your charitie, ſuppoſyng that they were the honoure, the worſhyp, the beautye of
<pb facs="tcp:4760:51"/>
the worlde, and that in them were all holyneſſe, and nothynge bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> holyneſſe that they were the lyghtes and lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternes of Chryſtes religyon, the very trewe patrones to folowe in all holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of lyfe, after whome men ſhulde fourine and faſſyon theyr lyues. And for that cauſe what ſome euer you dyd gyue to theym of your charytye, you thought it well beſtowed, ſuppoſynge that they take onely neceſſaryes for them ſelues, the reſydue to beſtowe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the beſt faſſyon. But it is not ſo (ſaythe Iude) as you thynke, they be not the honour and beautye of men, but they be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpottes that diſfygureth men, they be the peſtilence and deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to men, yf they be in wardly con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſydered. I graunte they be e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ampl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs and patrones, but of all euyll and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chefe. Of you they haue goten ryches and ſubſtaunce by crafte, by falſehede, hypocryſye and ſymulacyon: but as
<pb facs="tcp:4760:52"/>
they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>goten theyr goodes euyll, ſo they ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> them euyll, as the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon ſayinge is euyll goten euyll gone: ye ofte tymes it chaunceth, that thynge whiche is euyll gotten, to be worſe ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ence, rycheſſe gotten of your chary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye by hypocriſye and ſimulacion, they do not ſpende them in the feadynge of poore people in warkes of charytye, but in mutuall feaſtes to great men, to ryche men, byenge promotion and dignitye, gyuynge great rewardes to ſuche as nede not, to optayne fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oure of men they ſpende theyr rycheſſe in mutuall bankettynge and feaſtynge, in goodly &amp; delycate fare, in feadynge of horſes and dogges, I wyll not ſaye all. Theſe men all thoughe they be counted of the worlde to be the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noure and beautye of the worlde, and ſo they wolde be counted them ſelfe, yet ſaynct Iude here calleth theym the ſpottes and the deſtruction of Chriſtis
<pb facs="tcp:4760:52"/>
religion, and howe ſome euer they be counted with the worlde, they be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore god as ſpottes and fylthynes that diſfygureth. Yf any wyll conſyder theyr lyues (ſayth ſaynet Iude) they lyue without feare of god or of man, they lyue after theyr owne pleaſure and voluptuouſneſſe, other lyueth in great penurye and pouertye, in great labour, great payne, and in the ſwette of theyr browes gette theyr lyuynge full hardly. They lyue in great welth and abundaunce in ydelnes and plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſure, hauyng all thynges abundaunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly without any care or thoughte, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng no labours nor paynes to feade the flocke of Chryſt, and yet they wyll be theyr paſtors, and ſuffer their ſhepe to ſtray away from the folde, and to be a pray for the wolfe, foxe, and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyll, they wyll lay great burdens and yockes on other mennes neckes, but they them ſelues wyll not ones payſe
<pb facs="tcp:4760:53"/>
them with theyr fynger. Therfore not withoute a cauſe Iude calleth theym ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>s whiche lyue without all feare eatynge and drynkynge, paſſynge the tyme in ſporte &amp; game, takyng al their ple<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es here, as who ſhulde ſay, there were none other world after this, ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore they eate &amp; drinke and make good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, and take theyr pleaſure whyle t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ey are here, for after this world they thynke there is none other world, and yf there be any, what they ſhall haue there they can not tell, ſuche be the wordes of infideles, as appereth Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pientie. ii. To ſuche truly in an other worlde ſhall be ſorowe to their ſoppes payne and woo euerlaſtynge.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12b" type="verse">
               <head>Cloudes they are without wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter, caryed aboute of wyndes.</head>
               <p>Iude accuſeth theſe pſeudapoſtels of a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ogancy, they thynke them ſelues
<pb facs="tcp:4760:53"/>
to be cloudes, cloudes be a boue men, they moue in the ayre or element, ofty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes they obſcure and darke the lyght of the ſone from men, out of them com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth water that temporeth the earth, that maketh graſſe, and corne growe, ſo lyke wiſe theſe pſeudapoſtelles thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth them cloudes, that is to ſaye, that they are halfe Goddes, and aboue men and giue the water (that is to ſaye) doc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tryne that tempereth the earth, that is to ſaye all men be tempered, &amp; ruled by their doctryne, I graunte ſaythe Iude that they be cloudes as they counte the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues, but they be cloudes caryed of the wyndes hyther and thyther, they be inconſtant hauing no ſure doctrine for they be coſt this way and that way with euerye pufte and blaſte of wynde they be caryed with the winde, they be cloudes, but vnprofytable withoute water to temper the earth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is drye, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> is to ſay they want hole &amp; holſome doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryne
<pb facs="tcp:4760:54"/>
of god by the whiche they myght and ſhulde temper the thurſtie and dry Soules and conforte afflycted conſcy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences they be cloudes, but ſuche as dar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kens and kepe awaye from men the lyght of the ſonne, that is to ſaye they kep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> bake the truth of goddes worde, and wyll not lette it appere to men as muche as lyeth in them they darke the trueth of Goddes Goſpel by their tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicyons, by dremes, by inuencyons of men, whiche they commaunde and teach<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o kepe in the ſteede of Goddes worde, they leade vs from the lyght in to darknes, and wolde make vs to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue darcknes to be light. They bring vs from Goddes worde in our yough to gentylle authors whiche we muſte learne fyrſt, knowing well the bottell euer to ſmell of that lyquor whiche he fyrſt receyueth, yf we were brought vp ſoberly by a ſober and dyſcrete may ſter in gods learning, I ſuppoſe we ſhulde
<pb facs="tcp:4760:54"/>
euer ſmell of that liquor as Titus and Timotheus did. Saint Paul prayſeth their bringinge vp. i. Timo. iiii. ii. T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mo. iii. beſydes this that they leade vs out of the waye from Goddes lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng to gentyll authors, as to Ariſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, Plato, zenophon, and ſuche other, when we be paſſed them, then the way is ſtopped to Chriſt, but we muſt then go to dunce, dorobell, au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>royſe, bryco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, anthony, gabryell, thomas and ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>che lyke, and at the laſte when we ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>m to the ſtudy of holy ſcripture muſt be wraſted and wrythed after theyre myndes, &amp; their termes, and their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyll dyſtynccyons, althoughe they be neuer ſo farre contrary to the true mea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyng of the ſcrypture. Chriſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vs Iohan. v. to ſerche ſcryptures theſe cloudes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeth the contrary to ſerch doctors as gentyll authors, &amp; ſkole doctors as dunce dorobel petrus hiſyanꝰ &amp; ſuch like, holy ſcripture is to
<pb facs="tcp:4760:55"/>
be vnderſtandyd fyrſt by the ſcrypture it ſelfe, one place expoundeth an other, The holy ghoſt can beſt expounde him ſelfe. Seconde by the knowledge and phraſe of the tonges, as oflaten, grece and hebrue. Thyrdely by the expoſyci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the holy doctours that was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercyſed in ſcripture, as by the expoſyci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſainct Auguſtyne, Hierome, Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe, Chriſoſtone, Liprian, Lirill, and ſuche lyke, and theyr expoſycyons ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken where it agreeth with ſcrypture, and forſakynge where they agree not with Scrypture, as theſe Authours wolde their writynges to be taken as apereth in their workes, theſe authors wolde haue no man ſo addycted vnto theyr ſayinges, that what ſo euer they ſhulde ſpeke or had written y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it ſhulde be beleued as truth, and as an arcycle of the fayth, but they made y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcrypture of God to be iudge of their writinges.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12c" type="verse">
               <head>They be trees rotten in authum
<pb facs="tcp:4760:55"/>
vnfrutefull / twyſe deade / and plucked vp by the rotes.</head>
               <p>Iude compareth theſe pſeudapoſtels or falſe doc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ors to rotten trees in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e of harueſt, vnprofytable he calleth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, becauſe they bring furth no good frute but only occupieth the grounde where good trees ſhulde growe, theſe wyche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red trees be lyke to other trees whiche bringeth fourth good frute in tyme con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uenyent, theſe trees as other doth bud they brynge forth leues bloſſoms, and floures, but they be withoute frute in tyme of harueſt, then they be wethered not only vnprofytable without frute, but alſo they be twyſe deade to them ſelues and to other, that is to ſaye they brynge death to them ſelues, and alſo to other that beleueth them, they be as trees deade and plucked vp by the ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes as deade and rotten, ſo they beſuch as in who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e there is no hope of amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb facs="tcp:4760:56"/>
as in the tre pluckyd vp there is no hope that it ſhulde receiue rote and lyfe agayne. Trees that be wethered in harueſt do not liue agayn ne growe but they rote euer more and more, and at the laſt falleth downe deade, they be vnprofytable burdeins and lodes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth nother profytable to them ſelues nor other, ſuch be theſe pſeudapoſtels. Alſo they be as trees twyſe deade, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they lyue in themſelues, nor in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, they lyue nother in bodye nor in ſoule, they be deade in the rote, in the ſtocke, without lefe, without frute, for they be deade, that is to ſaye they haue nother true fayth hope nor charyte nor yet good workes, nor holſom doctrine to teache them ſelues and other, they be alſo trees plucked vp by the rotes that is to ſaye they be raſed oute from the boke of life, and cleane ſeparated from Chriſt, howe muche ſomeuer they boſt and crake them to be planted &amp; grafted
<pb facs="tcp:4760:56"/>
in Chriſte, and to lyue in Chriſte, and bringe furth frute that pleaſed Chriſte beſte, yet Iude ſayth they be ſeperated from Chriſt, and deade in Chriſt Iude is alwaye contrary to theyr proude o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pynion of them ſelues, whiche he labo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reth to plucke from them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13a" type="verse">
               <head>They are the ragyng waues of the ſee, foming out their owne ſhame.</head>
               <p>Iude contynueth ſtyll deſcrybyng theſe pſeudapoſtels, he calleth them the ragynge waues of the ſee, for as theſe outrageouſe waues fearſe and cruell doth toſſe the quiet and peaciable ſhyp nowe vp nowe downe, now this way nowe that waye, &amp; maketh the ſhyp &amp; them that be in it euer in parel of drou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning &amp; wyl not ſuffer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be quyet. But what doth theſe troubleſom wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſe, nothing els put fometh out
<pb facs="tcp:4760:57"/>
theyr foome and fylthynes, and theyr owne ſhame, ſo theſe pſeudapoſtels do troble and vexeth quiet and peaceable men, moore outragyouſe then the ſee, whiche ſomtyme ceaſeth of this outra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſnes and is caume. Theſe pſeud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>apoſtels be more outragyouſe then the ſee, for they neuer ceaſeth to troble, vex and dyſquyet thoſe that wolde lyue in quietnes &amp; peace. Theſe pſeudapoſtels ſtereth vp contencion, debate, and ſtrif they troble the common quyetnes, the common peace, they trouble the hoole worlde perſwadyng them ſelues to be the lyght, the lanterne of the worlde, theym to be the pooſtes and pyllers of Chriſtes church with the which Chriſt hath promyſed euer his preſence to the ende of the worlde, and that they can not erre, and yet their lyfe is contrarye to that lyfe that GOD requyreth of his church to whome he promyſed his preſence, and for this commeth ſuche
<pb facs="tcp:4760:57"/>
cumult, ſuch trouble in the worlde that men wyl not beleue them, ſaying they haue the preſence of god always with them, &amp; that they can not erre, nor god wold not ſuffer them to erre ſo longe, for this they rage, they rampe, they be wode, they troble all good men, &amp; theſe that wolde lyue quietly they vexe, they trouble, they do them iniuries, &amp; ſpeke euyll &amp; rayle on them ſhamefully: but in ſo doyng what gete theſe pſeudapo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtels to them ſelues? trewly nothyng els but that Iude here ſheweth, they fome &amp; ſpewe out their owne ſhame &amp; rebuke to their vtter co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Beholde to what purpoſe &amp; ende co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth theſe proude wordes of pſeudapoſtels? truly to their owne great ſhame &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſion, their craft, their ſuttelry, their hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſye is knowen well ynough, let them therfore halte no more before crepyls, their madnes ſhall be knowen to all men, as ſait Paule ſayth. ii. Tim<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. iii.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13b" type="verse">
               <pb facs="tcp:4760:58"/>
               <head>They are wanderynge ſterres, to whome is reſerued the myſt of darknes for euer.</head>
               <p>Alſo Iude calleth them wanderyng ſterres, becauſe they be wauerynge as theſe ſterres be, mouable &amp; inconſtant toſt &amp; moued w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euery winde, ſo be theſe pſeudapoſtels inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtant moued w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry wynde of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſſhe, or of deſyre of the world, &amp; be caryed whether y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deſyre of the fleſhe moueth them, alſo wauering ſterres gyues no lyght, but darkes the lyght of other ſtarres, &amp; letteth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lyght of clere ſterres, &amp; they be caryed of the wynde whether y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wynde bloweth: the nature of theſe ſtarres theſe pſeudapo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtels foloweth, men lyght in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dition, maners &amp; lernynge, whiche wyll go &amp; chaunge as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wynde bloweth, &amp; ſay as the worlde &amp; moſt part ſayth for lucres ſake, &amp; play Gnatoes parte very well as Terence doth ſay: what other men
<pb facs="tcp:4760:58"/>
ſay, they wyll ſay the ſame, and faſſion them ſelfe to the moſt parte, caryng no thynge what the trewth wyll or requi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reth, but rather what the heed rulers &amp; the multitude wyll &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeth, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though we knowe the moſt part to be ignorant of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> trewth: for many ſhal be da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pned, &amp; few ſaued: wherfore it is not always ſure to agre to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt parte.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13c" type="verse">
               <head>To whom is reſerued the myſt of darknes for euer.</head>
               <p>Now Iude ſheweth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> paine reſerued for theſe pſeudapoſtels &amp; mayſters of lies, the myſt of darknes, that is to ſay euerlaſtyng payne i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> darknes, &amp; where ſhal euer be darknes, wepyng &amp; gnaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of ceth. He doth appere to allude to them bryngynge in darknes to the lyght of trewthe, what darknes they bring to the light, no man can expreſſe ne ſhewe, and thoſe at the laſt ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue euerlaſting darknes in paynes. Iude here dothe feare men from ſynne
<pb facs="tcp:4760:59"/>
for feare of payne, ſhewynge ſynners that wyl not repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, not to eſcape euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting payne, whiche ſhal be in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to theyr great co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dempnacion &amp; pu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Therfore let no man thinke that he may ſynne &amp; eſcape all punyſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: for god of his iuſtice wyll not ſuffer ſynne to be vnpunyſhed in theſe that wyll not repent. In repentynge he forgyueth and pardonneth moche ſynne.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14-15" type="verses">
               <head>Enoch the ſeuenth from Adam ꝓphecied before of ſuche, ſaying behold the lord ſhal come with thouſandes of ſaynctes to gyue iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t agaynſt all men / &amp; to rebuke all that are vngodly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g them: of all their vngodly dedes whiche they haue vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted / &amp; of all their cruell ſpekinges whiche vngodly ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners
<pb facs="tcp:4760:59"/>
haue ſpoken againſt him.</head>
               <p>Leſt any man ſhulde thynke hym to haue ſpoken any newe thynge of theſe pſeudapoſtels to be punyſſhed, yf they do not repent, he bryngeth in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy of Enoch to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fyrme his ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ſayinge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Enoch was a good man the ſeuenth from Adam, &amp; that he ꝓphecied paynes and greuous punyſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tcs to come vpon euyll men, yf they dyd not repent. Alſo Enoch inſpired w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rite of god dyd prophecy the lord for to come w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> many thouſandes of ſaynctes (of the day of iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t he appereth to ſpeke) to gyue iudgement agaynſt all euyll men, &amp; to reproue them of theyr noughty wordes and dedes, of theyr noughty &amp; euyl wordes agaynſt god &amp; the profeſſers of his trewthe. Of the whiche ſayinge it is euydent that god wyll reproue in that day as well euyl wordes as euyll dedes.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4760:60"/>
Alſo Iude here certifieth vs, that the day of iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t wil come, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which day god wyll rewarde good men with hye rewardes: &amp; euyll men with euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtynge punyſhement. He wyll come to iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t hauyng with hym many thouſandes of his ſayntes: in the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che day there ſhall be ſhewed as well the euyll wordes, as the euyll dedes of euery man, and ſhall be made open to all the worlde. Of the whiche wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des and dedes euery man ſhall make a counte for hym ſelfe: and yf they haue done well, they ſhall receyue a rewarde: yf they haue done euyll they ſhall be commytted to payne and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſſhement euerlaſtynge. Iude here threttenynge payne euerlaſtynge to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyll men dyd no newe thynge, for E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noch the ſeuenth after Adam dyd the ſame. Alſo here is to lerne the goodnes of god, whiche prouydeth in all tymes ſom good men, which diſſwadeth men
<pb facs="tcp:4760:60"/>
from ſynne for feare of punyſhement, and alſo whiche hathe ſhewed mercy, grace &amp; remiſſyon of ſynne to be onely of god that all truſt and al confidence ſhulde be put in god.</p>
               <p>This place of Iude ſcarſe in any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place of ſcripture is founde, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſome of the fathers longe dyd re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecte this pyſtell of Iude, but this is not ynoughe to reiecte a booke or a pyſtell for one or other ſentence, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che do not differ from other places of ſcripture: yf y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſentence dyd differ from ſcripture, then it were a cauſe outher to doutte of it, or to reiecte it, or elles no. Saynt Paule brynngeth in Ian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem and Mambrem. ii. Timoth. iii. whiche were the wytches of Pharao, whiche reſyſted Moyſes Erodi. vii. ſuche men there were, whoſe names be not expreſſed Exo. vii. ſaynt Paule nameth them, ſhall we ſaye that theyr names be not as ſaynct Paule calleth
<pb facs="tcp:4760:61"/>
theym, becauſe theyr names is not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in any other place of ſcripture, that is no ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t cauſe to ſay ſo, or to reiect ſai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Paules piſtell to Timothe, it is ſufficient that ſaynt Paule dothe ſay it, whom we knowe dyd ſpeke by the holy gooſt, &amp; the ſpiryte of god.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="verse">
               <head>Theſe are murmurers, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners walking after their owne luſtes, whoſe mouthes ſpeketh proude thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges, they haue me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in gret reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s bicauſe of aua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tage.</head>
               <p>Iude ſome thynges omytted before now he addeth of theſe pſeudapoſtels, affirmyng them to be murmurers &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>playners. Yf any man wolde ſpeke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their vſurped power, ſay they, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wold deſtroy al holynes, al vertue &amp; al goodnes, whiche only minyſheth their power falſly vſurped, if any man ſhal omyt any thing of their olde tytle, by and by they crye out, &amp; ſay that god
<pb facs="tcp:4760:61"/>
and all his Sainctes is deſpiſed, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned, and ſet at nought, they cry the contempte of god, and diſobedyence to his churche, when no man contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth god, nor is diſobedyente vnto the churche of god, nor diſobedyent to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge that god wolde haue men obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyente to. Furthermore they be mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murours agaynſt god and his diuyne power yf any afflyccyons, incommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dites, mynyſſhyng of their authorite &amp; ruell, of their hye tytles and ſuche lyke ye they be not affrayed to murmure a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt god, that he ſuffereth ſuche thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges to chaunce vnto them, contrary to their myndes.</p>
               <p>Theſe perceyuinge theyr lyues to be very ſhorte, they murmoure in their hartes that god created of ſo ſhorte life ſubiect to ſo many infirmytes and ſyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, wyſſhynge and deſyringe them to lyue euermore in this corporall bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy in pleſure as they nowe lyue with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oute
<pb facs="tcp:4760:62"/>
any payne, and of the lyfe to come vtterly deſpayringe, meaſurynge all felycytye and pleaſure of thys bodye. Theſe pſeudapoſtelles be murmurors and complaynors yf euerye thynge do not come to paſſe after their mynde, as God were to be blamed that he punyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth not ſtraytely theym that reſyſtich and gaynſayeth their noughty wyll, and couetouſe mynde. They murmure agaynſte the truth knowne, whiche o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peneth and ſheweth theyr hypocriſy &amp; ſymulacyon longe hidde by the which they haue deceyued the worlde longe. They murmoure that they can no len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger kepe the ſymple chriſten people in ſuperſticyon, falſe and fayned holynes the cauſe of theyre murmurynge is by all coniectures, that they can not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe their ryches and ſubſtaunce no more by hipocriſy ſimulacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> falſe and fayned holynes. Their murmuringe ſheweth that they be not content with
<pb facs="tcp:4760:62"/>
their ſtate and callyng. They murmur agaynſt other, when agaynſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue men iuſt cauſes to murmure &amp; to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playne, ſayenge they lyue after theire proper concupyſcence and pleſure of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſſhe and not after the wyll of god.</p>
               <q>whoſe mouthes ſpeaketh proud thynges.</q>
               <p>What boſtynge wordes and full of vanite they do ſpeake ſo far wide from the truth. They ſaye they haue power in body &amp; ſoule, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they may make lawes to bynde mens conſciences vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the payne of deadly ſyn, but Chriſt ſayth that men hath power in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> body, to kyll y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoule they can not ſaith chriſt Mat. x. feare not he ſaith theſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> kyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the body, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoule they can not kyll they haue not y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they may do more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> kyll the bodye. Furdermore they ſaye they haue two ſwerdes, a ſpirytuall ſwerde &amp; a temporall with the whiche they may ſmyte whom they lyſt, &amp; whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4760:63"/>
they luſt, contrary is this their proude ſayeng to ſainct Paul. Ro. xiii. which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeth euery man to be obedienc to the cyuill powers, which not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a cauſe bereth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſworde to ponyſhe euel doars to make good me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to lyue in peace and quyetnes. Agayne they ſaye they be exempted from al kynges, prin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cys and rulers, from all trybute or cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum to be payde to Kynges, Princys, Emperors, and that by their owne ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empcyon fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all obedyence of hye pow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ers and rulers. And not onely thus they haue exempted themſelues, but al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo they haue exempted many other, as many relygyouſe howſes, many cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes gyuyng to themſelues vnder lead annuyte and exempcyon, in ſo muche that it is not lawfull for Lyuyll offy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers to meddell with a relygyouſe ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or to correcte any fault of a religyouſe man, ſuche be their proude wordes of vanyte, whiche they ſpeake.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:4760:63"/>
               <q>They haue men in greate reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence becauſe of auauntage.</q>
               <p>Theſe pſeudapoſtels prayſeth and laudeth men aboue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mone, of whome they loke to haue lucre and vauntage, be they neuerſo euel, neuer ſo wycked them they wyll prayſe and laude, them they wyll flatter ſayenge good to be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell and euell good, ſwet to be bytter and bytter ſwet, darknes to be lyght, and lyght to be darknes, iuſtyfyenge the euell for money, to whome the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet Eſay doth thret wo euerlaſtynge. Eſaie. v. ſayenge wo be to theym that ſayth good is euell &amp; euell good, ſwet to be ſower and ſowerſwet, darknes to be lyght and lyght darknes, iuſtify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enge the euell for money, theſe be flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers whiche ſpeake not thoſe thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges whiche the Goſpell teacheth, but they ſpeake flattery and thoſe thynges that pleſeth them of whome they hope to haue lucre, vauntage, or hye promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="tcp:4760:64"/>
or dignite. Eraſmus in his tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacyon hath a meruaylouſe worde, he ſayth they maruayle at, or they haue perſons in admiracion for a vauntage (as who ſhulde ſaye) they laude, they praiſe, they extol perſons, ye they make them halfe a god and all for lucre ſake ye or equall with God, and far aboue all men, hath not the Popes decrees made the Pope aboue men, and as he were a god, loke in the decrees and ye ſhall fynde it. Do not they make the pope as a god, whiche geue authoryte to the biſſhop of Rome to interpret ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſcrypture after his pleaſure, and as he interpreteth ſcrypture that it muſte nedes be taken, and ſo vnderſtande, and that it is not laufull to diſcent fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his interpretacyon? do not they make the pope as a god, which ſayth that he hath authorytie to bynde &amp; looſe, what he wyll in Heauen, and in earth, and at hys pleaſure, when the Byſſhoppe
<pb facs="tcp:4760:64"/>
of Rome, or any other Byſſhoppe can not bynde or lowſe, but after the wyll and pleaſure of god? do not they make the pope as a GOD, which gyue lyke authoryte to the decrees of the pope, as to goddes worde, goddes commaund<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, theſe men I ſuppoſe deſerueth a byſſhoppryche or a cardynallſhyp, for their flattering, for their lyes, ſuche be they of whome Iude here ſpeaketh, whiche haue men in admyracyon for aduauntage.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="verse">
               <head>But ye dearly beloued / remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the wordes which were ſpo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken before of the Apoſtelles of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſte / ho we that they tolde yo we / that there ſhulde be begylers in the laſte tyme whiche ſhulde walke af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their vngodly luſtes.</head>
               <p>Iude intendynge to make an ende
<pb facs="tcp:4760:65"/>
of his piſtell exhorteth them to whome he wrote, to remember the wordes of the apoſtelles of oure Lorde Ieſus Chriſte, whiche ſayde that there ſhulde come begylers and deceauers, ye moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers ſkorners, and deſpyſers of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des worde, whiche do deſpyſe and ſet at nought the worde of god preferring mannes doctryne aboue the preceptes of God, or at the leeſt makynge man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes worde equall with goddes worde to auoyde and fle theſe men, and their falſe doctryne, Iude here exhorteth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and alſo when there ſhulde come ſuche men y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wolde deſpyſe and ſcorne god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des worde, that they ſhuld knowe that to be the laſte tyme, and that theſe thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges were fulfylled, whiche the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtelles of oure Lorde dyd ſpeake before theſe falſe prophetes dyd come, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> men monyſſhed of them before, ſhulde bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter knowe them, and auoyd them, and be ware of theym, and theyre doctryne.
<pb facs="tcp:4760:65"/>
Here the apoſtell byddeth vs reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre the wordes of the apoſtels of our lorde, he byddeth vs not remembre this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cre or that decre of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> byſhop of Rome, to remembre this religyon or that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligyon, this cuſtome or that cuſtome, this ſayinge or that ſayinge of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: but he byddeth vs to remembre the wordes of the apoſtels of our lorde, and after theſe wordes to warke and lyue all our lyfe tyme. He byddeth not vs here loke what this cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cell or that cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cel haue decreed, what the churche of Rome haue ordeyned, what the reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of man hath inuented: but what the apoſtels of our lorde Ieſus Chryſt hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded vs in their writinges to be kepte, and to be fled &amp; eſchewed, theſe thynges as neceſſary to be done, other thynges as charitie of thy chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten brother requireth. Some there be that thynke this pyſtel was not writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of the apoſtell of Ieſus Chryſt, for
<pb facs="tcp:4760:66"/>
theſe wordes that he exhorteth theym here to call to remembraunce the wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des of the apoſtels of Ieſus Chryſte? To this may this anſwere be made, that it may well ſtande togyther, the author of this pyſtell to be an apoſtell of Ieſus Chriſt, and alſo that he exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth them to call to remembraunce the wordes of the apoſtelles of our lorde Ieſus Chriſt, and that for dyuers cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. Fyrſt that he dyd the ſame thynge here that the apoſtels of Ieſus Chryſt dyd, as ſhulde appere by theyr wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynges &amp; wordes. Secondly to teache all other to confyrme theyr doctryne by the doctryne of Chriſt and his apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtelles. Thyrdely to confute the falſe doctryne of the pſeudapoſtels, whiche coulde not be proued by the wordes of Chryſte and his apoſtelles, his owne name or hym ſelfe he dyd not expreſſe becauſe of humylitie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="verse">
               <head>In the laſte tyme there ſhulde
<pb facs="tcp:4760:66"/>
come begilers which ſhuld wal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke after theyr vngodly luſtes.</head>
               <p>He ſayth begylers ſhulde come in the laſt dayes ſpoken of before of the apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtelles of Ieſus Chryſt, that men mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſſhed of theym ſhulde the better be ware of theym and of theyr doctryne. But who be they whome the apoſtell monyſſheth here them to take hede of and to be ware of. Fyrſt they be theſe that contempneth, deſpyſeth, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth a ſcoffe of the teachynges of holy ſcripture, and cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teth them as folyſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and vanite, mocketh and ſcorneth the ſayinges of holy ſcripture, and ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth holy ſcripture &amp; the profeſſors of it theyr mockyng ſtocke at tauerne or alehouſe, at their ryot &amp; feaſtyng, &amp; byd<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deth men ſticke to their olde traditions of fathers, ſaying all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> olde ſhall come agayne. I ſuppoſe they wold ſay y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> byſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Rome with all his traditions
<pb facs="tcp:4760:67"/>
ſhall come agayn, yf they durſt ſay ſo: but this thynge is to be coniectured they meane ſo ſaying. Secondly theſe whiche lyue not after the wyll of god ſhewed in ſcripture, but after their car<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nall deſyre and luſt doth lyue in ydel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, welth and pleaſure, nothynge re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardyng the lyfe of the ſoule. Thyrd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly theſe whiche ſeparate them ſelues from god, and brynge in a newe ſecte denyeng the lord whiche hath bought theym, of whome it is ſpoken. ii. Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tri. ii. Fourthely theſe that be beaſtly men not vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyng thoſe thynges whiche are of god, but whiche are of fleſſhe, not beleuynge the great reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of all that be deed, not bele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng the iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of that great day, not beleuyng any lyfe to be after this lyfe, hauynge no faythe to holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but beynge as horſes and mules whiche hath no vnderſtandyng. Fift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly theſe that haue no ſpiryte of god, no
<pb facs="tcp:4760:67"/>
mynde to good thynges, but ſet theyr myndes to all myſchefe, to all vnhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pynes contemnyng all heuenly thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and immoderately deſyrynge all worldely thynges, yea lyuynge ſo in pleaſure as there were neyther god ne deuyl, neyther heuen nor hell, neyther lyfe nor deathe, neyther pleaſure nor payne after this lyfe. Therfore the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtell Iude ſayth they be makers of ſectes, naturall, hauynge no ſpyryte that is of god, yea no ſparke of godly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, as is before ſhewed, therfore I do paſſe ouer that ſentence.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20-21" type="verses">
               <head>But ye derely beloued edyfye your ſelues in your mooſt holy fayth praying i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the holy gooſt / and kepe your ſelues in the loue of god, lokyngc for the mercy of our lorde Ieſus Chryſte vnto e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall lyfe.</head>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4760:68"/>
Iude contynueth ſtyll in his exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, deſiryng them to go for wardes in fayth, byldynge theym ſelues vpon fayth by the holy gooſt, prayeng in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryte, kepynge them ſelues in charite &amp; loue of god, warkynge the warkes of charite, kepyng vnite, concorde, peace, pacience, as well in aduerſite as i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperite, lokynge for the mercy of god, whiche bryngeth to euerlaſtyng lyfe, whiche life doth not come of our war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, merytes, nor deſeruynges: but by the onely mercy of god, as teſtifyeth ſaynct Paule ad Titum. iii. ſayenge, Not of the warkes of iuſtyce whiche we haue done, but by his mercy he hath ſaued vs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22-23" type="verses">
               <head>And haue compaſſion on ſome, ſeparatynge them / &amp; other ſaue with feare, pullynge them out of the fyre / and hate the fylthy veſture of the fleſſhe.</head>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4760:68"/>
Iude here ſheweth certayne offices of charite towardes ſynners, and firſt he teacheth howe it beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth men to vſe them ſelfe towardes ſynners that be not obſtynate, nor obdurate in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyce. Secondly as touchynge obdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate ſynners. Fyrſt as touchynge all ſynners, it becommeth no man to be gladde, to reioyſe of any ſynne, of any vyce in any man, but to be ſory for all vyce and for all ſynne done, or iniury done to any, or by any man. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, gentylneſſe, mercy, pytye, compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyon, and pardon is to be vſed in ſuche as by neglygence, by ignorance, and by infyrmytye of nature be fallen to ſynne, to rebuke them ſoftly and gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tylly for theyr ſynne, to ſhewe theym the daunger of it, to exhorte theym to forſake theyr ſynne, and to abhorre it, to take and enbrace vertue, and to ſhewe the fruytfull commodytyes of vertue and of goodneſſe. And this is
<pb facs="tcp:4760:69"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4760:69"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4760:70"/>
to be done as longe as there is hope of amendemente. But yf ſo be that they be ſo obſtynate, &amp; ſo obdurate in malyce, that they wyll by no gentyll exhortation, nor gentyll admonition be plucked from theyr noughtyneſſe, but wyll contynue ſtyll in errour, in hereſye, and in noughty doinges, then be you ſory for theym, praye god for theym to conuerte and mollyfye theyr obſtynate hartes, and turne theym to ſome grace, ſeparate your ſelues from theym, haue no medlyng with theym, let theym be clere ſeparated from the company of good men, that they may be at the laſt confounded and aſhamed with theym ſelues, ſeynge that euery good man forſaketh theyr companye, and that for theyr noughtyneſſe. Let this thyng be done with all diligence, and with all humanitye. Let nothyng be omytted in you of your dewtye to wynne them, and at the leſt that theyr
<pb facs="tcp:4760:70"/>
ſoules may be ſauffe in the daye of the lorde, yf it be poſſyble.</p>
               <p>Many there be whiche ſore com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playneth of ſome men called ſpirytu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all men for theyr tyrannye, crueltye, and vnmercyfulneſſe, as touchynge ſuche as hathe erred from the faythe, from the goſpell, and from holy cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes receyued, whom they ſaye the byſſhoppes hath burned, not offeryng mercy, pardon or gentylneſſe to them, whiche thynge they thynke to haue ben a great cauſe that they were ſo ſtyffe in theyr euyll opynyon, for the whiche they haue ſuffered deathe for, or els bycauſe the punyſſhement was ſo opprobryouſe that they ſhulde haue ſuffered. Yf they wolde haue forſaken theyr euyll opynyon, that they hadde leuer haue dyed, then to haue ſuffered ſuche an opprobryous punyſſhement, whiche ſhulde haue ben an immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall ignomynye to his name for euer,
<pb facs="tcp:4760:71"/>
and to haue ben a cauſe that no man ſhulde haue gyuen credence vnto his wordes afterwardes, yf he hadde ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken neuer ſoo trewe, and nothynge but the goſpell of god. Peter denyed his mayſter Chryſte and dyd forſake hym, and ſayd he neuer knewe hym, and that with an othe. Afterwardes he was penytente, and God dyd for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyue hym hys ſynnes, he was not compelled to beare a faggotte for his offence, for to be a ſygne of an immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall ignomynye of his name. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore, yf God ſhulde punyſſhe vs for euery lyttell faute or offence done agaynſt his goodneſſe, and make vs repentynge to beare a faggot, I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe there wolde be many faggottes borne in a yere, or elles fewe repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. I do not here ſpeake of ſuche as hathe ben impryſonned, and vngen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tylly and vnmercyfully handeled by ſome ſpirytuall men, not for errours
<pb facs="tcp:4760:71"/>
or hereſye, or for theſe thynges that haue ben co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to the holy ſcripture, contrary to the worde of god, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to holy cuſtomes receyued, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to ſuche thynges as agreeth with goddes worde. But for wordes ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken agaynſt abuſes of thynges vſed, and becauſe they haue ben vſed, the ſimple vnlerned people and vntaught thynketh men to ſpeake agaynſte the thynges vſed, when men ſpeaketh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt the abuſes. And of that it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth that dyuers trewe preachers is and hath ben endited of ſymple people of hereſye, as they call it, when theſe ſymple people dothe not knowe whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is hereſye, whiche is the goſpell, whiche is trewth, whiche is falſehede. Therfore yf it wolde pleaſe the hye powers and rulers (to whome it per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayneth to do) to mytygate the rygo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſneſſe of that lawe whiche to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nytent perſonnes deputeth that they
<pb facs="tcp:4760:72"/>
ſhuld beare faggottes, or els chaunge that punyſſhemente in to ſome other punyſſhemente: and alſo wolde pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſſhe all accuſers and ſclaunderers of other for hereſye with lyke punyſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, yf they coulde not proue it. For nowe many men be accuſed and be ſclaundered of hereſye, and that for malyce, for enuye, for deſyrynge men to do theyr dewtyes, to preache and teache the people of god gods worde, to fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>de with it, as the people dothe feade them with tythes of theyr bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyces. For this cauſe men be euyll ſpo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken on, haue iniuryes done to theym, be ſclaundered and be accuſed of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roure and hereſye: and ſuche men be accuſed whiche be beſt learned, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che hath taken mooſt paynes to ſette forth Goddes worde trewly, purely, and ſyncerely, whiche neuer in alle theyr lyues dydde preache erroure ne hereſye, whiche I dare be bolde to ſay
<pb facs="tcp:4760:72"/>
doth loue error or hereſye worſe then any of them that doth accuſe hym, ſuch as be ydle them ſelues, and wyll take no payne, no labours to teache theire flocke co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mytted to their cure, but wyll ſyt all the daye and night at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tauerne at ale houſes eatynge, drinkynge, fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtynge, and makynge good chere, and at cardes, and dyſe paſſynge the tyme in pleaſure, and then is a tyme con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenyent to ſpeake euell, to rayle, to ſlau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der, to accuſe true preachers, good ſtudentes that wolde ſomthyng with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawe them from their good chere and make them ſaue their ſoules in the day of the Lorde yf it wolde be. Therfore I ſuppoſe verely yt ſhulde auoyd gret tumult, greate ſlaunder, ſhamefull ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſacyons of error, or hereſy, ye I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it ſhulde be greately for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon welth, yf hye powers and rulers wolde make legem talionis, that is to ſaye, that they that ſlaunder or accuſe
<pb facs="tcp:4760:73"/>
other ſhulde be punyſſhed with lyke punyſſhement, as hereſyes be, yf they coulde not proue theyr accuſation.</p>
               <p>This lawe ordynated ſhulde ſtoppe moche falſe ſclaunder, moche falſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation, moche trouble of innocentes and poore men: it ſhulde make goddes worde to be preached all abrode pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſyncerely, it ſhuld ſtoppe many ſclau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derous and poyſonfull mouthes, whiche now care not what they ſpeke of other, howe they ſclaunder other, what poyſon cometh out of their mou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes of other, it is vnpunyſſhed.</p>
               <p>An other offyce of charitye there is to delyuer from the mouth of the deuyll thoſe that be begyled, deceyued, or by other wayes drawen in to errour or hereſye by the doctryne or meanes of falſe doctours, to delyuer theſe from errour, from hereſye, and ſo from hell fyre, it parteyneth vnto charitye, of the whiche ſaynct Iames dothe ſpeke. Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobi.
<pb facs="tcp:4760:73"/>
v. ſaying. Bretherne yf any man among you hath erred fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the trewth, and any man ſhall conuerte hym, let hym knowe that he whiche hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted hym from his errour ſhall ſaue his ſoule from deathe, and ſhall couer many ſynnes. Iames alſo here dothe not appere that he wold that that man whiche by ignorance, by neglygence, by infirmytye of tonge or of man hath erred from the trewthe in to ſome er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roure whiche he hathe vttered by his mouthe, and ſhewed by ſomme other good man that he was in an errour, whiche after he knoweth to be errour, he is ſory for it, that he helde or defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ſuche an opynyon that was erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyouſe, or any wayes contrarye vnto the trewthe, whiche opynyon contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye vnto the trewth he forſaketh, and taketh gladly with a good mynde the trewth, ſaynct. Iames doth not appere to ſaye that he wolde that that man
<pb facs="tcp:4760:74"/>
ſhulde beare a fagot for ſpeakynge of his erroneus opynyon, but he is more mercyfull then ſo, as oure ſauyour Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus is mercyfull to vs all, and maketh vs not to beare fagottꝭ for euery faute but forgeueth vs wyllyge vs no more to offende. Thirdely Iude here ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth what thynge we ſhulde hate in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerye ſynner (that is to ſaye) his ſpot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted cote of the fleſhe, that is to ſaye his vyces and ſynnes, not the man ordina<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted and created of God, but his euel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, as Paule teacheth vs Roma. xii. hate you ſayth he, that whiche is euell and loue that is good, euell therfore is only to be hated, and good to be loued, and thys is it that Iude calleth the ſpotted cote of the fleſſhe, becauſe all theſe ſpottes commeth of the infirmyte of the fleſſhe.</p>
               <p>This laſte ſentence of Iude the olde tranſlacyon hath moore playnly then Eraſmus tranſlacyon hathe, he
<pb facs="tcp:4760:74"/>
ſaith, reproue you them iudged that is to ſaye, reproue them as worthy to be iudged, ſhewe them obſtynate and as condempned and noughty perſonnes worthy to ſuffre puniſſhment for their ſynnes &amp; obſtynacy in ſynne: the other that be not obſtynate, but by infirmite of nature fallen vnto ſynne, ſaue and pul them from the fyre of hell, whiche commyth to ſuche as wyll not repent, and forſake theyr ſynne.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24-25" type="verses">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto hym that is able to kepe you / that you fall not and to pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſente you fautles before the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of his glorye with Ioye / that is to ſaye, to God our ſauy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our whiche only is wyſe be glo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rye / mageſtye / domynyon / and power nowe &amp; for euer Amen.</head>
               <p>Here Iude maketh an ende of his Epyſtell gyuinge thankes vnto God
<pb facs="tcp:4760:75"/>
whiche only is wyſe oure Sauyoure whiche maye kepe vs clere from all ſynne, and make vs withoute ſpottes or wryncles in the ſyght of his glorye and maye make vs only to reioyſe in hym and not in oure ſelues, nor in no other creature but only in God, which hath called vs before the begynning of the worlde, that we ſhulde be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and withoute all ſpottes of ſynne, yea faureles in his ſyght, as Paule teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyeth. Ephe. i. to God which is only wyſe be all honoure, glorye, Imperye, domynyon, nowe &amp; euer worlde without ende</p>
            </div>
            <closer>AMEN.</closer>
            <trailer>The ende of Iudes pyſtell.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:4760:75"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>printer's device (?) of Thomas Gibson</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>¶ Imprynted in the houſe of Thomas Gybſon.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
